<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tyranny and hypocrisy detected or, a further discovery of the tyrannical government, popish-principles, and vile practices of the now-leading Quakers. Being a defence of the letter, intituled, The spirit of the hat, against the deceitful, defective and railing Answer, called The spirit of Alexander, &amp;c. With a challenge, to refer the judgment of matters of fact to the verdict of twelve impartial judges, equally chosen. Also, many of their letters, papers, and transactions among themselves are made publick; wherein they contradict one another, and attribute titles to George Fox, that are proper only to Christ.</title>
            <author>Mucklow, William, 1631-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51569</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3036</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201177</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825124</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825124</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29497</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51569)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29497)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2174:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tyranny and hypocrisy detected or, a further discovery of the tyrannical government, popish-principles, and vile practices of the now-leading Quakers. Being a defence of the letter, intituled, The spirit of the hat, against the deceitful, defective and railing Answer, called The spirit of Alexander, &amp;c. With a challenge, to refer the judgment of matters of fact to the verdict of twelve impartial judges, equally chosen. Also, many of their letters, papers, and transactions among themselves are made publick; wherein they contradict one another, and attribute titles to George Fox, that are proper only to Christ.</title>
                  <author>Mucklow, William, 1631-1713.</author>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
                  <author>Mucklow, William, 1631-1713. Bemoaning letter.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Fr. Smith, at the Elephant and Castle in Cornhil, near the Royal Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By William Mucklow, author of The spirit of the hat.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Penn, William.  The spirit of Alexander the copper-smith lately revived, now justly rebuk'd, or, An answer to a late pamphlet, intituled, The spirit of the hat, or the government of the Quakers.</note>
                  <note>With order at end of text on appropriate Quaker dress, by George Fox.</note>
                  <note>McAlpin Catalogue reports: Appended to his Spirit of the Hat: 1673, with continuous register, but separate pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reprinted in 1700 with the title: "A bemoaning letter" (Wing M3033).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Penn, William, 1644-1718. --  Spirit of Alexander the copper-smith lately revived --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Mucklow, William, 1631-1713. --  Spirit of the hat --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29497:1"/>
            <p>TYRANNY AND HYPOCRISY Detected: OR, A further Diſcovery of the Tyrannical-Government, Popiſh-Principles, and vile Practices of the now-Leading <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BEING A Defence of the Letter, intituled, <hi>The Spirit of the Hat,</hi> againſt the Deceitful, Defective and Railing An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, called <hi>The Spirit of Alexander, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>With a Challenge, <hi>To refer the Iudgment of Matters of Fact to the Verdict of Twelve Impartial Iudges, equally choſen.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo,</hi> Many of their Letters, Papers, and Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions among themſelves are made publick; wherein they contradict one another, and attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute Titles to <hi>GEORGE FOX,</hi> that are proper only to <hi>CHRIST.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But they ſhall proceed no further: for their folly ſhall be made manifeſt unto all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Fr. Smith,</hi> at the Elephant and Caſtle in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the Royal Exchange, 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:29497:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:29497:2"/>
            <head>Tyranny and Hypocriſie detected.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>OW dangerous a thing it is for a man to ingage himſelf publickly for any ſingular party upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Religion, is greatly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in the leading <hi>Quakers,</hi> and eſpecially in <hi>W. Pen,</hi> from whoſe Parts and Education one would expect more than ordinary Candor and Ingenuity: but having imbarked himſelf among thoſe People, (who alſo by their Tenets are peculiarly diſpoſed to have a high opinion of themſelves, and to contemn all others) and having obtained a high repute among them, he betakes himſelf to ſuch pitiful ſhifts, ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilities and bravings to uphold their detected Cauſe and tottering Kingdom, as one would think could not proceed from any man profeſſing Chriſtianity. He that would have this evidently proved, let him read his late controverſal Writings, eſpecially his <hi>Winding-ſheet,</hi> and <hi>Spirit of Alexander.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the Spirit of the now-<hi>Quakers</hi> or <hi>Foxonians,</hi> detected to be none of Chriſt's, by ſeverall Pieces that have come forth of late; at length the Book in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled <hi>The Spirit of the Hatt</hi> made publick, diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers their principles and practices in their government amongſt themſelves, to be far different from what
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29497:3"/>
they profeſs openly when they invite people to be <hi>Quakers:</hi> and that they act upon the ſame princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and in the ſame Tyrannical manner (as far as their power reaches) as the Court at Rome: And this not only proved by inſtances of matters of fact, ſeen and heard for the moſt part by the Author himſelf; but alſo argued and compared with that principle which was held forth as the foundation of their way, and upon which he (certainly not one of the leaſt ingenious among them) became a <hi>Quaker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What was now to be expected from theſe men thus detected, may be ſeen in their <hi>Spirit of Alexander the Copper-Smith,</hi> or <hi>Anſwer to the Spirit of the Hatt;</hi> which I ſhall in ſhort make ſome remarks upon.</p>
            <p>And firſt we may obſerve, that (like contentious women) where the matter is moſt evident againſt them, there they make the grateſt noiſe, and are moſt clamorous and furious; and make the greateſt ſhow of confidence and victory: when the deſign of their owne vain-glory and greatneſs is manifeſted not onely by thoſe that have conſidered them in their publick appearance; but alſo by ſome within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that are privy to their <hi>Cabals</hi> and private tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions, then <hi>the Divil</hi> muſt needs <hi>be hard beſet, and his condition deſperate;</hi> ſee <hi>Spt. of Alex. p.</hi> 1. becauſe the foundations of their Kingdom ſhake, and their ſubjects diſcover it, and ſeek to withdraw themſelves from their territories. Who could have made a more apt inference from ſuch premiſes?</p>
            <p n="2">2. That though they call this Author's Relation, <hi>Lies, Forgery, Defamation,</hi> with abundance of terms of the like <hi>Foxonian</hi> leaven, yet when they come to particulars, they either, 1. confeſs what they deny
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29497:3"/>
with an idle diſtinction, (except ſome few things;) or, 2. Acknowledge them by ſaying nothing concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them; or 3, uſe ſome deceit in their terms of denial, which every Reader cannot diſcover; or 4. take an occaſion from ſome circumſtances, perhaps not rightly ſet down, to deny the whole matter.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That <hi>W. P.</hi> doth in their names acknowledge that the ſubſtance of this Authors complaint is true, (H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es p. 14, 15. in his p. 8.) namely, that <hi>they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him to yeild</hi> [to their determination againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="7 letters">
                  <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
               </gap>ience] <hi>becauſe the Body would have it ſo, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat was yeilding to the Power.</hi> And he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> oppoſition to the Author, <hi>That his not ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> but perſiſting, is diſſention; but their diſown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> [excommunicating and depriving of a liberty of marrying, burying &amp;c.] <hi>any perſon for that cauſe, is no breach of the great Goſpel Charter of Liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is that which <hi>W. P.</hi> labours to do, and for that purpoſe uſeth no other Arguments than the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in the like caſe, who are the onely perſons that I know of that challenge ſuch a power; for the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants do not challenge it: the <hi>Church of England</hi> challenges onely a prudential power of determining ſome Ceremonies, as of the Surplice, Croſs and Knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, to be convenient at this time: but not by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of an infallible Spirit, or as of Divine Authority; which the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> do, and the <hi>Quakers.</hi> As for the Arguments that this Author urges againſt this uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, <hi>W. P.</hi> paſſes them by, and gives, inſtead of anſwers, clamours and railings againſt him. As for the Arguments that <hi>W. P.</hi> uſeth, they being the ſame with thoſe of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> againſt the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> they may be found anſwered and refuted every where in Proteſtant writings.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:29497:4"/>4. But that which this Author doth chiefly inſiſt on, and which indeed is moſt proper for him, and the choice and proſecution of it renders him Ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, is, That in this Doctrine and Practice of theirs, they manifeſtly contradict the chief principle and main foundation they at firſt held forth, whereby they have commended themſelves to the world, and have gained to be their Proſelytes ſome honeſt hearted people, and among the reſt this Author. For indeed the <hi>Quakers</hi> chief principle, namely, <hi>That every one ought diligently to take heed to, and walk according to the Light in himſelf,</hi> is of ſuch evident truth in the plain ſenſe of the terms, that there can ſcarce be found either Chriſtian or Heathen, (that underſtands what he ſaith) that can deny it; for it is in ſubſtance this, <hi>That every man ought diligently to obſerve and do what God doth by any meanes convince him to be his Duty.</hi> Now conſidering that this was cryed up by the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> as the old Truth brought to light by them, 'twas no wonder that their Doctrine was received by ſome wel-minded people, that were not ſo happy as to know themſelves aforehand to be poſſeſſors of this common principle; and there's no queſtion but all of them that do it honeſtly, do it upon the ſame ground: But herein lyes <hi>the myſtery</hi> of their iniquity, (which this man has been ſo ingenious and happy as to diſcover,) namely, <hi>That he who ſhall receive the forementioned principle as evident in his own heart, ſhall afterward be induced to believe that whatever the cheif Quakers teach, is as evident, and that this evidence is from the immediate Revelation of God's infallible Spirit within himſelf.</hi> But if it happen that the leading men contradict one another (notwithſtanding they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the infallible Light to be their guide) then he that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29497:4"/>
has the ſtrongeſt intereſt among the Elders ſhall judg the other party, and if he or they do not ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to this judgment, he ſhall be condemned in the name of the Lord, and deprived of all both Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick and civil priviledges, which they can by any means hinder him of. And beſides, if he make any publick complaint, and do not conform to their wills, they will then load him with all poſſible reproaches, and rather than fail, they'll ſay he is broken in his brain or diſtracted, as they did of <hi>John Pennyman;</hi> ſo if he be a man, who in reſpect of his Trade or Calling, doth depend upon them or thoſe they have intreſt in, he and his family ſhall be pitileſsly ruined. This is the ſubſtance of what this Author has ſet forth, and which <hi>W. P.</hi> defends.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Now who this Author is I know not, and I do not perceive him concerning himſelf to make any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to the <hi>Quakers</hi> railings; perhaps he thinks (as the truth is,) that his vindication is ſo evident to every one that will but impartially read his Letter, that there's no need of more. For who can otherwiſe than preſume this man capable of giving a juſt and true ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the <hi>Quakers</hi> chief principle upon which himſelf was owned, and receiv'd by them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued with them ſome years? And 2. who can read and not clearly perceive that the practice he found among them doth abſolutely ſubvert that principle? For if every man muſt upon pain of ſin walk accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>the Light in his own particular,</hi> then he cannot without ſin walk according to <hi>the Light in</hi> G. Fox,<note place="margin">See Cont. Dial. p. <hi>63, 64, 65.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>or other Men,</hi> when that is contrary or diverſe from his own.</p>
            <p n="6">6. As for my ſelf and other Chriſtians, this Letter
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29497:5"/>
ſerves us moſt effectually to prove, 1. That theſe <hi>Quakers</hi> their crying up <hi>the Light within,</hi> or <hi>the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible rule and guidance of the Holy Spirit in every particular Conſcience as the ſupream Judge,</hi> is but a ſhooing-horn to draw people in, and that when they are brought over to them by that means, then they muſt be ruled and guided by the judgment of <hi>G. Fox</hi> and the ruling Elders: So 'tis manifeſt, They preach that in their Doctrine, which they contradict in their practice. 2. That ſome <hi>Quakers</hi> (and it's more than probable that the moſt of them) believe and practiſe by tradition and imitation of their Leaders, perſwading themſelves in the mean time that they are taught by an infallible Light in themſelves ſo to do. 3. That the Body of the <hi>Quakers</hi> conſiſts of ſuch a ſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite Beleivers; for when this man and his Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons gave themſelves ſo much liberty as to examine things to find a particular conviction, they could find no ſuch thing; and its eaſy to perceive by his reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he is more able to examine things than one of a thouſand of them. So that, 4. Quakeriſme properly is not built upon that Principle rightly underſtood, viz. <hi>Every man ought to believe and practiſe according to the Light in himſelf;</hi> (for in that reſpect we and all honeſt men are <hi>Quakers,</hi>) but upon a falſe and miſtaken notion and ſenſe of it, viz. That <hi>what the leading men teach for the Light in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, is indeed ſo.</hi> 5. This inſtance gives a full anſwer to that common evaſion of the <hi>Quakers:</hi> when we plead that we alſo walk according to the Light of God in us, they preſently reply, that <hi>we are of the world, and in the cuſtoms and reaſonings of it; but if we would come out of the world, and be obedient as they are, we ſhould experience the Truth, as they do:</hi> Well! we
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29497:5"/>
have here an experienced man (and he's not alone) that has given obedience (as they) to the Light in himſelf, which becauſe it contradicts the will of <hi>G. Fox</hi> and the Ruling-Elders, he is diſowned by them. Now then, 'tis evident they would not have us to follow the Light in our ſelves, but the Light in <hi>Geo. Fox,</hi> &amp;c. and that the Aſſurance and Infallibility from Experience they talk of, is meerly a ſtrong Confidence in <hi>G. Fox</hi> and his Companions.</p>
            <p n="7">7. But to come to the particulars of the Cauſe; <hi>We are beſpatter'd</hi> (ſaith <hi>W. Pen,</hi> p. 4, 5.) <hi>becauſe we abhor, renounce, and rebuke with ſeverity that rude Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">G. F. <hi>did not ſo in the Book, entituled,</hi> True honour amongst the Jews, <hi>p. 7.</hi> And is not this Cap-honour from below, and worſhiping the Beaſt and Dragon? <hi>And p. 9.</hi> For the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Hat is a will-worſhip.</note> 
               <hi>Hat on in publick Prayer, which did we uſe, we ſhould but be eſteemed by you</hi> [Profeſſors] <hi>the worſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Very likely, Sir; But do you order your ſelves in the Worſhip of God by the reaſon of gaining our eſteem? Why do you not anſwer your Friend's Argument drawn from your own Principles? You acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a Reſpect and Reverence due unto Magiſtrates; but you deny them that of the Hat: why? <hi>Becauſe it's low and periſhing, and may be trampled on, there's no ſolidity in it; The Hat-honour, Hat-worſhip, Hat-humility is an honour below: but men that be in the Law of God, they mind not the Hat;</hi> G. F. And will you give that as a reverence to God, which you ſay is too low for men? Doth <hi>G. Fox</hi> ſay in Print to them that keep on their Hat at your Prayers, <hi>You give no more reverence unto God than unto a Horſe;</hi> and yet keep it on before Princes and Governours, to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29497:6"/>
whom he allows at leaſt more reverence than to a Horſe? But whence is the obligation of putting off the Hat at Prayer? The <hi>Quakers</hi> do not pretend the Authority of the Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.4. <hi>Every man praying or propheſying with his head covered, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoureth his head;</hi> And <hi>John Perrot</hi> has long ago urged that againſt them: For if it be unlawful to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the head in Prayer, 'tis ſo alſo in Propheſying or Declaring, which notwithſtanding they practiſe: if the one be lawful, the other cannot be unlawful. And <hi>why</hi> (ſaith our Author) <hi>ſhould it be lawful to have the head covered when a Miniſter returns high praiſes to the Lord, and matter of Excommunication to do the ſame in time of his Prayer?</hi> p. 33. We ſay, There's no Divine Command for it; it becomes an outward token of reverence to God from the cuſtom of the Country that uſeth it for ſuch toward men. Therefore in the Eaſtern Countries where they uſe it not for a reverence to men, neither do they uſe it to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God, but have their heads covered at publick Prayer. <hi>G. F.</hi> p. 10. <hi>The Jews did not put off their Hats when they went into the Synagogues or Temples, &amp;c.</hi> P. 11. <hi>The Prieſt was not to uncover his head in the Sanctuary</hi> (Lev. 21.10.) <hi>which is contrary to the Prieſts now in the Temples.</hi> P. 4. <hi>And the Turks count it an odious or hateful practice to put off the Hat: (yet they are to honour.)</hi> How come then the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> who abhor the Cuſtoms of the World, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain this in the Worſhip of God? Did <hi>G. F.</hi> in this matter forget himſelf? or, had he a ſpecial Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for it? A ſpecial Revelation without doubt, if it be true that he doth nothing without one; Well! that's enough to juſtifie him in ſo doing: But how comes he <hi>to require other men to practiſe it, when they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29497:6"/>
are not convinced of it?</hi> O (ſaith <hi>Pen) I utterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce that, in our Friend's name, as an infamous ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: But</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we will be well ſatisfied with any Members diſpractice of an orderly performance, once cheerfully owned. p.</hi> 10. Is not this a deep-ſtudyed Man think ye, that could find out ſuch a learned diſtinction? Nay, but probably he will pretend he writes by Revelation: So then, they do not require Men to practiſe what they are not convinced of: but they require men not to diſpractiſe what they are not convinced of. I had always thought that two Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives in Engliſh make an Affirmitive; and ſo, that <hi>not to diſpractiſe</hi> is the ſame as <hi>to practiſe:</hi> Let the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed world vail to <hi>W. Pen!</hi> But he means that they require men <hi>not to leave off to practiſe, what they have practiſed:</hi> (what! though they practiſed without conſideration, or conviction? Yes:) <hi>That is</hi> (ſaith Pen) <hi>moſt reaſonable and orderly,</hi> P. 10. If once you become a Quaker, and do, as they do, let the induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be the Opinion you have of <hi>G. Fox</hi> or what it will, if ever you diſſent from them in the leaſt Ceremony, you are an Apoſtate, and ſhall be dealt with accordingly; as it ſeems our Author was.</p>
            <p n="8">8. But how will <hi>W. Pen's</hi> learned diſtinction ſerve the caſe of the Maid? who being required of <hi>John Bolton,</hi> by vertue of an Order from <hi>G. F.</hi> to few up the ſlit in her Waiſtcoat-skirt behind, anſwered that <hi>ſhe ſaw no evil in it;</hi> and <hi>James Claypole</hi> thought it ſutable to their principle, <hi>that ſhe ſhould firſt ſee the evil of it in her ſelf, before ſhe judged it, and not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>becauſe we ſay it: But the poor man</hi> (as ſaith our Author, p. 29.) <hi>was fain to acknowledge his error in it, though in private he confeſt it</hi> (to <hi>G. Welch,</hi> of which 'tis believed <hi>John Oſgood</hi> is not ignorant) <hi>to be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29497:7"/>
no error:</hi> But I know not how it comes to paſs, but <hi>J. Claypole</hi> is as ſubtile in diſtinguiſhing here as <hi>W. Pen</hi> himſelf: <hi>The intent of my words</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>was, that every one ſhould be left to God's Witneſs in their Conſciences, to condemn what that condemns, and to juſtifie what that juſtifies, and not to condemn or juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie barely upon the motion or judgment of others.</hi> This he aſſerts: and the Slander he denies is this; <hi>That the Tyranny of their Elders is ſuch, as to impoſe upon the weak and ſimple that which they cannot believe:</hi> And the miſapprehenſion upon which he was called to judgment was, <hi>as if</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>my words had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended ſo far, as that nothing was to be accounted an evil, unleſs the guilty party ſaw it to be ſo.</hi> The Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is touching a thing not in its own nature evil, the meaning muſt be this; <hi>That the ſlit in the maid's waiſtcoat muſt be accounted an evil, becauſe G. Fox had judg'd it to be ſo;</hi> and the made muſt few it up, (as many others had done upon the ſaid Order) though ſhe her ſelf ſaw no evil in it. What now doth this come ſhort of <hi>requiring to practiſe before conviction,</hi> or <hi>impoſing upon the weak what they cannot believe,</hi> except they be reſolved to believe as the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievs? Are theſe men fit to be talked to, that dare affront the world with ſuch deceiful defences as theſe are? Is this your glorious liberty, ye members of the <hi>Quakers</hi> Body? That if ye ſubmit not to the Law of <hi>G.F.</hi> or the ruling-Elders, ye ſhall be accounted <hi>Belialites</hi> and <hi>in the Spirit of Ranteriſm, ranting Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> and to be dealt with accordingly! <hi>The beſt words utter'd from Chriſt in the dayes of his fleſh,</hi> (ſaith G. Keith) <hi>and yet recorded in Scripture, cannot reveal the Father:</hi> but it ſeems the words of <hi>G. F.</hi> or the Elders can reveal the Fathers will, even in things po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29497:7"/>
and ſo are of greater efficacy and authority than Chriſt's. He that can ſay any thing, can recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile theſe things with what <hi>W. P.</hi> ſayth in his caveat againſt Popery, p. 8. who, ſpeaking againſt <hi>the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations of general Councills, as requiſite to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſibly obey'd,</hi> inferr's, that ſo <hi>the morall or doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall good or evil of an Act or principle (in and from a mans owne judgment) ſhall not be obliging; but he muſt be bound againſt his owne ſenſe, reaſon and faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. Now I think the liberty, or rather ſlavery, the <hi>Quakers</hi> are in one to another, is manifeſt; Let us next ſee what liberty they allow to the world; that is, to Chriſtians who are not of their Body, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to Presbyterians, Independents, Baptiſts; to them <hi>G. F.</hi> will not allow liberty, becauſe they are not <hi>in the Power or Truth:</hi> But <hi>W.</hi> P. never wants a <hi>Salvo</hi> for <hi>George,</hi> let him ſay what he will: <hi>He meant it</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>not of outward but of inwardly Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty:</hi> And yet <hi>W. P.</hi> knew it was ſpoken to one, (at a meeting at Devonſhire-houſe) who pleaded for Liberty of Conſcience about his Hat, which is an outward exerciſe; But why we ſhould imagin they would give Liberty, whoſe both Principles and and Practices are againſt it, I know not; of both which we have in theſe ſheets a fair account. For, 1. They pretend to an infallible Judgment in all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, whereby the poſſibility of being in Truth to Perſons differing from them, is quite taken away. 2. They account him a <hi>Ranting Spirit,</hi> who ſhall not account that evil, (even in matters of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony) which they account evil, <hi>after due admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp;c.</hi> And is it conſiſtent with any Government in the World to tolerate <hi>Ranters?</hi> 3. They do fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29497:8"/>
impute to men thoſe crimes as manifeſt, that are juſtly puniſhable by the Magiſtrate; ſuch as are, <hi>Malicious Acts, Slanders, Injurious Lying, Deſigns to Miſchief, Injuſtice, a Murdering Mind, Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Villany, &amp;c.</hi> So that if <hi>W. Pen</hi>'s reaſoning againſt the Baptiſts in his Epiſtle before <hi>Plain Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp;c.</hi> be valid, then the Quakers will certainly perſecute; for thus he ſaith, <hi>But this notably ſhews their ſpirit, who thus adventure to perſecute</hi> [viz. <hi>by revilings] without power: Let who will believe they would not do it if they had power; for my own part</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I declare my ſelf none of that number.</hi> Now I appeal to the ſober judgment of all men that are converſant in reading Books, whether they ever met with any writings ſo full of reviling and il-bread lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage upon ſuch ſlight grounds as thoſe of the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers.</hi> 4. It's ſo notoriouſly true what this Author ſaith, <hi>that he hath ſeen pulling down, haling out, and thruſting forth of their Meetings, and that they went as far as their Power, and conſequently wanted not Will, but Power, to puniſh:</hi> Yea, it's ſo manifeſt to thoſe that have uſed their Meetings, that <hi>W. P.</hi> in appeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God's holy Witneſs in all Conſciences for their vindication, diſcovers himſelf a man greatly to be lamented as either blind or impudent. Let <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Chadwel</hi> tell of the uſage he has found amongſt them. Have they not added <hi>puſhing, pinching, kicking,</hi> and <hi>hard-treading upon feet and toes</hi> to thoſe other violences? But <hi>W. P.</hi> anſwers, that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver refuſed Conſcientious Inquirers, and would be informed, <hi>if ever they ſo uſed any conſcientious Inquirer or oppoſer.</hi> Let us name who we will, I dare warrant he'll never allow any of them to have been conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. I have ſeen ſome Papers of one <hi>William King</hi> a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29497:8"/>
               <hi>Quaker,</hi> and who upon that account has expoſed himſelf to impriſonment for ſpeaking in the <hi>Quakers</hi> Meetings. But he complains of the ſame uſage from the <hi>Quakers</hi> as from their perſecutors; that he has been hal'd down out of their Gallery in Grace-church-ſtreet with ſuch violence that he has ſcarce felt the ſtairs; that <hi>he has often felt their cruel hands;</hi> that <hi>G. Whitehead,</hi> being in a great rage and fury at <hi>Jer. Clerk's</hi> houſe, gave him a ſore pinch in the arm; that they would not ſuffer him to be a priſoner (tho for the ſame cauſe) among them, but procur'd that he ſhould be keept in the common-priſon, with a great deal to the ſame purpoſe: Now becauſe he doth in ſome things diſagree with their judgment, they deal with him in this manner: Nay, moreover, he ſaith, <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> and others came to <hi>Henry Pawſon</hi> and his wife, with whom he lodged, and charg'd them not to entertain him, thereby indeavouring what they could to force him out of the Land. Now perhaps they will ſay <hi>W. King</hi> is a mad man; if he be, they ought to ſhow more compaſsion towards him and not to deal with him in that cruel manner they do; but for my part I ſee nothing in his Papers, which doth not become a <hi>Quaker,</hi> and is not ſutable to their Principles. There are ſeveral other Inſtances of their uſing Violence in their Meetings, which may be urg'd as occaſion ſhal ſerve; And their Paper againſt <hi>John Pennyman</hi> when he was in Priſon, may ſhow what ſpirit they are of. Nay, they would not ſpare that grave ancient Gentlewoman <hi>Anne Mudd,</hi> who being moved to ſpeak a few words among them, before their Speakers began, <hi>Thomas Matthews,</hi> who guarded the ſtairs, pulled her away by violence. Theſe are the People that in former dayes have vex'd
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29497:9"/>
and diſquieted all ſorts of Religious Aſſemblies with their Meſſages (as they ſaid) from the Lord, and have clamour'd againſt thoſe as Perſecuters, that could not otherwiſe obtain their peace than by thruſting or carrying them out; and yet themſelves do the ſame and worſe, not only to thoſe of a contrary mind and Judgment, but alſo to thoſe of the ſame Mind and Principle, even when they profeſs (as themſelves) to be moved thereto of the Lord. The <hi>Jews</hi> at <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> permitted the <hi>Quakers</hi> to ſpeak in their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, but that the <hi>Quakers</hi> will not allow others. They have profeſſedly denied to permitt any of their Religion to marry a Chriſtian, or one of the world, how honeſt and pious ſoever, if not in their way; Witneſs <hi>Oliver Holmes, W. Mucklow</hi> and many others: And <hi>W. Pen</hi> owns it as a peice of, not only juſt, but neceſſary puniſhment to be inflicted upon him that is not a <hi>Quaker,</hi> or him that is ſo in all things but the Ceremony of the Hat in Prayer, that if he could not get a wife ſave among the <hi>Quakers,</hi> he ſhould never have one: See his p. 10. where he calls ſuch an one's diſſent, <hi>Imaginations and Whimſeys. As for their denying ſuch an one a burial, though they would deny it him alwayes as one of them, but eſpecially their now uſurping his property in a burial-place, is</hi> (he ſayth) <hi>a down-right forgery.</hi> Kindneſs! They would not ſuffer ſuch an one to ſtinck above ground, but he ſhould be buryed, not among the Catholicks, but as Hereticks in <hi>Spain</hi> or <hi>Italy:</hi> But it is ſo notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and common with them (as they that have been among them report) to deprive ſuch diſowned per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of their property in the burying-place, that I wonder with what face they can deny it, or what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion they can have for it. Did they not <hi>Tho. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:29497:9"/>
and did not <hi>J. Bolton</hi> deny it to <hi>W. Musklow</hi> &amp;c. Did they not make void from the Hat-men (as they called them) the Notes they had for the uſe of the Burying-place preſently after the Papers of Orders by the 11 Elders? and did not theſe men's money pay for it?</p>
            <p n="11">11. As for <hi>John Oſgood's Cabbaliſtick Harangue,</hi> which is pretended to be <hi>for the clearing of God's Truth and People,</hi> in the matter of his concern, it's ſo far from that, that it confirms what is ſaid by our Author againſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> but ſhews that <hi>John Oſgood</hi> is now, by joyning with them and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming a Preacher among them, become another man; ſo that inſtead of complaining againſt, (as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly) he ſeeks to cover, the iniquities of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: For whilſt he doth in general terms deny all, he doth in particular deny nothing at all. Read p. 30, 31, 32. of <hi>the Spirit of the Hat,</hi> and he either ſayes nothing to thoſe things that are there related, or confeſſeth to that which he would ſeem to deny. He ſays p. 21. <hi>the oppoſition he had, related not to his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, as a Marriage, or to hinder his proceed therein: but that the Meeting could not paſs it, as their approve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he being not in unity with the Meeting as to that matter aforeſaid,</hi> viz. of giving teſtimony againſt the Spirit of the Hat, which he did already in his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice diſapprove. And what doth our Author ſay more? and how could this acute man ſay, <hi>the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing would not hinder his Proceed in his Marriage, when they would not approve of his Marrying, without which Approvement he could not legally proceed?</hi> But the Mother of his Bride, <hi>Rebekah Trevers,</hi> being a great Mother and Governeſs among them, cryes out then in her own and Daughters concern, that <hi>their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29497:10"/>
cruelty was worſe than that of the Biſhops;</hi> and ſo by her Authority, and <hi>J. Oſgoods</hi> Intereſt, they proceed to Marriage without Licence; which was ſo offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to <hi>John Bolton,</hi> that he publickly diſowned <hi>Tho. Salthouſe</hi> (one of their Miniſters) for being a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to it, and for his Moderation.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Let us now proceed to other Inſtances men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in <hi>the Spirit of the Hat,</hi> whereby it will evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appear, that the great zeal, labours and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of the leading <hi>Quakers</hi> tend chiefly to their owne ambition, and to the obtaining of a Lordly po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer &amp; domination over the Perſons and Conſcience<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of their Proſelytes: and that they uſe moſt wicked wayes and means for accompliſhing theſe ends. And that which firſt offers it ſelf in this ſervice, is that inſtance of <hi>G. Fox</hi> menioned p. 28. which the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> in their <hi>Spirit of Alexander</hi> &amp;c. ſay nothing to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and therefore we may well conclude it for truth, and that they had nothing to ſay in excuſe of it; for it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a moſt conſiderable charge againſt the Man of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> adoration, whom they can ſcarce mention without a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Epithet of praiſe, as, of, <hi>innocent, good, holy, uprigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Man of God, Prophet indeed,</hi> and the like: Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaying of <hi>S. Eccles,</hi> cited by our Author, wherein that which is ſpoken of Jeſus, or the True Light <hi>Job.</hi> 1.10. is applyed to <hi>G. F.</hi> who is alſo ſaid to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>that true Prophet, whom John ſaid he was not;</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is no other but Chriſt; This Blaſphemous Teſtimony was complained of by ſome of the <hi>Quakers</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but they could not prevaile that it might b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> recall'd, for <hi>G. Fox</hi> had approv'd it both before and after it was printed; but they got <hi>S. Eccles</hi> to writ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an explication of it, which made the matter ſo muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the worſe, that it was thought good to ſuppreſs tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:29497:10"/>
And notwithſtanding, theſe complaints from ſeveral hands, yet I never could hear that <hi>G. Fox</hi> reprov'd him for it; but he made him one of his ſelect Diſciples to accompany him in his travels for the propagation of his Goſpel in <hi>America.</hi> Where (as is related in the Account of his proceedings read in the <hi>Quakers</hi> Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting here at <hi>London</hi>) he ſent for at one time an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour and two Kings to come and hear him, and they gave their attendance to the great Prophet <hi>G. Fox, at whoſe name</hi> (as was writ formerly by one of their Miniſters) <hi>even the Heathen tremble.</hi> The ſaid <hi>S. Eccles</hi> at a publick Meeting celebrated him in theſe words: <hi>Bleſſed be the man that came out of the North: Bleſſed be the womb that bare him, and the paps that gave him ſuck:</hi> And <hi>Joſiah Coal</hi> an eminent <hi>Foxonian</hi> Miniſter writes thus to <hi>G. Fox</hi> from Barbado's.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>21 <hi>day</hi> 12 <hi>month.</hi> 1658.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Dear <hi>G. Fox,</hi> who art the Father of many nations, whoſe life hath reach'd through us thy children, even to the Iſles afar off, to the begetting of many again unto a lively hope, for which Generations to come ſhall call thee <hi>Bleſſed;</hi> whoſe being and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation is in the power of the Higheſt, in which thou <hi>rules and governes</hi> in Righteouſneſs, and thy <hi>Kingdom</hi> is eſtabliſh'd in peace, and the increaſe thereof is <hi>without end.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This great Prophet (I ſay) is charg'd by our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor with opening Letters and altering the Contents, that he took a Letter of <hi>John Whiteheads</hi> (a moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Miniſter among the <hi>Quakers</hi>) which was writ by him (as he ſaid) in the name of the Lord, and blotted out a line or more, and wrote, or cauſed to be
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29497:11"/>
writ, to a quite contrary ſenſe, to wit, <hi>That he did judge thoſe that kept the Hat on, and not thoſe that kept it off,</hi> (or words to this effect) whereas <hi>John Whitehead</hi> did therein <hi>juſtify both thoſe that kept it off or on, &amp;c.</hi> This Letter was (as I am informed) ſent into <hi>Holland</hi> to the <hi>Quakers</hi> there, which comming to the hands of <hi>Benj. Furly,</hi> he diſcovered the forgery, and it was ſent back again; and being complained of at a private Meeting by <hi>John Osgood, William Penington</hi> and <hi>John Pennyman</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>John Bolton</hi> putting on't to <hi>John Whitehead,</hi> whether he did not give <hi>G. Fox</hi> liberty to alter it, ſaid, <hi>No,</hi> not any liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to alter a ſubſtance, which he ſaid that was, and at another time ſaid he was abuſed therein, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Let the world ſee by this Inſtance from what Spirit it is theſe men ſpeak and write in the name of the Lord, when they can ſo flatly contradict one another! (more of this afterwards.) Let the world ſee alſo the <hi>Quakers</hi> way of anſwering Books, when they can ſlip over ſuch a charge as this againſt their chief Prophet, which containes in it, that which, for the nature and kind of it, is one of the greateſt crimes that mortals can be guilty of. 'Tis the ſame with that of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira</hi> his wife, (<hi>Act.</hi> 5.) which the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> animadverted upon them by a miraculous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction of Death: for as he and his wife conſented to bely the Holy Ghoſt, (as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> allows, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther learned men ſenſe it) to wit, by pretending an inſpiration and motion from the Spirit of God for the doing of that which they had no inſpiration for, and knew they had none: So alſo <hi>G. Fox</hi> doth in this Letter make <hi>John Whitehead</hi> with the Holy Spirit to write that in the name of the Lord, which <hi>G. F.</hi> knew that neither he nor the Spirit did write any
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29497:11"/>
ſuch thing, but the contrary. Thus he doth at once belie both <hi>John Whitehead</hi> and the Holy Spirit of God, and that knowingly. For I do not doubt but the <hi>Quakers</hi> do frequently write and ſpeak that in the name of the Lord, and as from his infallible Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which is falſe, but they perſwade themſelves, it is true; but here we have <hi>G. F.</hi> writing that for the words of the Lord, and the judgment of the infallible Spirit in <hi>John Whitehead,</hi> which he himſelf knew to be falſe. O Prodigious Impudence! He that counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits any mans name in a matter of any concernment deſerves to be expoſed on a Pillory, and to loſe his ears: how much greater puniſhment doth he deſerve that counterfeits both the name of God and man, in a matter of religious concern? Neither may they here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after pretend, in their excuſe for this omiſſion, that <hi>G. Fox,</hi> the man chiefly concern'd, was abſent; for both <hi>John Bolton</hi> and <hi>Samuel Newton</hi> (two Zealots againſt the Hat-men) were both preſent at the ſaid private Meeting, and ſtood in the juſtification of the alteration, and others that are here preſent know very well the circumſtances of this buſineſs; and it's like ſome of them, as well as <hi>G. Whitehead,</hi> were privy to the aforeſaid forgery, as <hi>Sapphira</hi> was to that of her husband <hi>Ananias.</hi> This is the courſe that <hi>G. F.</hi> took to make his injunctions be obſerved as well in <hi>Holland</hi> as in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. The next inſtance ſhal be that of <hi>M. Bowman</hi> and <hi>Eliz. Baily,</hi> mentioned <hi>p.</hi> 33. Now you muſt know that <hi>G. F.</hi> and his Peers have, under pretence <hi>of good and comly Order,</hi> at length injoyned all <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> that will marry, that they firſt come before the Meeting and refer the matter to them, and acquieſce in their determination, who will be ſure not to paſs
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29497:12"/>
it, if the party deſiring Marriage, one or t'other, differ from them in the leaſt Ceremony, as appears in that of <hi>J. Osgood,</hi> that of <hi>W. Mucklow,</hi> and in that of <hi>Oliver Holms</hi> and<note n="*" place="margin">An honeſt plain Couple came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Mens Meeting, deſired to be married. Their Integrity was fully attested: yet, becauſe the Man could not ſay (after Prayer and Fasting for reſolution in the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion) that he thought it an evil to go and be married with the Prieſts according to the Law, they would not paſs it. Others they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed for carrying great Guns in their Ships: and yet <hi>John Thomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> a Quaker, Maſter of a Ship, owned by <hi>G. R. S. N.</hi> and other Quakers, not only carried Guns, but fought ſtoutly, and killed many of the Dutch before his being taken.</note> others, alſo in this I am about; for it ſeems <hi>Eliz. Baily</hi> was a thorow <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> and <hi>M. Bowman</hi> differed very little from a <hi>Quaker,</hi> and had teſtimony given of him that he was a ſober man, and no Hypocrite, but was not yet in the full practice of all their little Ceremonies, for he would ſometimes put off his Hat in Salutation. Theſe two came before the Mens Meeting and found ſo much favour among them that ſome of the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers <hi>declared poſitively, as from the Lord, that it was to paſs: whereof one</hi> Tho. Briggs <hi>was tranſported with ſuch an angry zeal,</hi> that he told the oppoſers, <hi>it was of the Lord, and they oppoſed the mind of the Lord.</hi> But the poor man was ſo far from knowing the mind of the Lord in that matter, that he did not know who the Perſons were of whom he ſpake; others of the Elders oppoſed it, having on their ſide the authority of <hi>G. Fox's</hi> Order; the conteſt between them was high and long, and in this diſſention they parted for that time. To this relation, as ſet down by our Author, the Anſweres ſay nothing, and ſo we ſhall take the truth of it <hi>pro confeſſo,</hi> and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29497:12"/>
make ſome improvement of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. We may ſee by this what the infallibility is which theſe Leading-men ſo highly glory in: It is onely a daring confidence whereby they aſſert things to be infallible and in the name of the Lord upon ſuch weak grounds as other men cannot build a ſtrong probability upon.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. That they do even in their Meetings blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the Name of the Lord, a ſin not leſs than Murder or Adultery, and which was (under the Law) to be puniſhed with no leſs puniſhment, even Death: See <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.20. For whilſt they contradict one another in the Name of the Lord, of neceſſity one of the Parties (what ever the other) doth blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme God's Name.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. That this Contradiction which they aſcribe to the Name of the Lord, is a proper effect of their preſent principle, as underſtood by them: for whilſt they aſſert that every <hi>Quaker</hi> is to follow the immediate teaching of the Light in himſelf as the infallible will of God, and have no way or means by their principle to diſcern one immediate teaching from another; and are manifeſtly, by reaſon of their Education, Paſſions and Intereſts, diverſly inclined in judging; it is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally impoſſible but that (eſpecially in leſſer matters) they ſhould have contrary ſtrong perſwaſions, which they muſt account the Teachings of the Lord, and aſſert in his name: and by this and other inſtances we ſee by experience it is ſo. And hence,</p>
            <p n="4">4thly, We ſee clearly what our Author aſſerts, That in the determinations in their Aſſemblies, when there are any hearty and conſcientious diſſenters, they apoſtatize from their principles, and betake themſelves to the principles and practices of the Church of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29497:13"/>
               <hi>Rome,</hi> giving the final judgment of their faith and duty to that Party, man, or men among them, which ſhall have the greateſt Intereſt in their eſteem, or by advantage of his witt, confidence, zeal, arrogance, &amp;c. can over-power and ſubdue the reſt. Therefore we ſee here when the Elders were ſomewhat equally di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, they could not come to any determination; ſo in <hi>Perrot's</hi> caſe and his Party about <hi>the Hat,</hi> whilſt <hi>Perrot's</hi> party was ſtrong and numerous, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in credit, they permitted them to uſe their liberty; then in <hi>Rich. Hubberthorne's</hi> anſwer to <hi>Jo. Parrot's</hi> Paper about the Hat, ſent by <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> to <hi>I. P.</hi> at <hi>Iſaac Penington's,</hi> and which was approved by <hi>G.F. &amp;c.</hi> were theſe words, <hi>Then no ſuch reaſonings had we had, if ſo be the free Spirit of the Lord had been minded, which is not to be limitted neither to the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Hat, nor off the Hat in time of Prayer.</hi> And in the year 1661, there was a Meeting at <hi>W. T's</hi> Houſe with <hi>G. Fox. F. H. G. W. R. H.</hi> and <hi>J. Perrot</hi> about the Hat, they ſuppoſing that <hi>Jo. Perrot</hi> had injoyned the keeping of it on in Prayer, which he denyed, and declared both by words and writing, <hi>that he did leave all to the free univerſal Spirit</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and made not a Law for any man.</hi> So it was concluded upon by them all, that there was to be no impoſition on either hand, but every one was to be left free there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: Of this <hi>J. Osgood</hi> and many others are witneſſes. But when <hi>Perrot</hi> began to decline and loſe his credit, then <hi>G. Fox</hi> and his Party take the advantage, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn his principle and practice, require conformity of all that will be own'd for members of their Body, that is, that will not be excommunicated, &amp; accounted Ranting Spirits, as <hi>G. F. J. B. &amp;c.</hi> called them. The Papiſts place Infallibility in the determination of One
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29497:13"/>
Pope, or One Council, or One Pope and Council to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: But theſe Quakers place <hi>Infallibility</hi> in every particular Perſon, and conſequently no other Perſon or Perſons whatſoever have any power to determine againſt him, for ſo an equal ſhould have power over an equal, an infallible over an infallible, which is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd: For a Body conſiſts of particular Perſons, every of which is no more infallible one than another; and there being many together, adds nothing of infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to them, becauſe infallibility is the higheſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, and doth not admit of degrees. So that a ſingle Perſon that is infallible is not more or leſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, becauſe many or none are of his mind: And if this particular Perſon may err, that alſo, and every one of that Body; conſequently there can be no infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible deciſion of any controverſy between them, but that which is made by number, intereſt, force, cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or the like, none of which will any man in his witts ſay, is any ground of infallibility, except upon the Arguments of the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>W.P.</hi> ſaith, that God hath given greater judgment to his Church than to the individual members of it, is a true poſition, and the Church of Rome errs not in that, but in accounting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a true Church.</note> Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which quite ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the Quakers principle.</p>
            <p n="5">5thly. We ſee by their aſſuming to themſelves the power of judging in ſuch matters, &amp; by their ſeverity in enforcing thoſe things that tend to their Being and Reputation, as a diſtinct &amp; eminent Body, even againſt their primitive principles, that their deſign is not (as one would have thought at firſt) to engage people to a diligent obſervance of the Light in their own Conſciences, but to make them acquieſce in thoſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29497:14"/>
things, as the infallible Law of God, which they ſhall judge fit for the getting and maintaining of credit and glory in this world. What elſe can poſſibly provoke theſe men thus to oppoſe the Name of the Lord to the Name of the Lord? Suppoſe equity and Right on the one ſide, which made them aſſert it in the Name of the Lord; there muſt be ſome ſtrong luſt on the other ſide, or elſe they would never have dared to oppoſe the Name of the Lord, and pretend his name too for ſo doing: and what could that luſt be, but that of dominion, arrogance and glory among men? The deciding of ſuch a matter as this man's marriage upon the point controverted between them, could not I think have any other tendency.</p>
            <p n="14">14. I have been the longer upon theſe two inſtances becauſe the matter of fact in them is not denyed: now we come to that which is, or rather ſeems to be denyed, or is deceitfully ſo. I mean that relation of a Paper ſent to <hi>Hartford,</hi> mentioned p. 18. In anſwer to which three <hi>Quakers</hi> of <hi>Hartford,</hi> namely <hi>Henry Stout, Nicholas Lucas, Richard Martin</hi> teſtify that <hi>in God's fear they know of no ſuch Paper, ſo ſigned, or ſent, conſequently there could be no ſuch contents or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like:</hi> And they conclude <hi>that five great and manifeſt lyes meet in</hi> thoſe few lines of our Author; 1. <hi>that there was ſuch a Letter;</hi> 2. <hi>that it had that paſſage in it;</hi> 3. <hi>that twelve of the great Ones ſigned it;</hi> 4. <hi>that it was diſliked; and laſtly, that he remembers all this.</hi> We ſhall now ſhew the great diſingenuity and deceitfulneſs of this anſwer. For</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt, Our Author doth not ſay that <hi>Twelve of the great Ones,</hi> &amp;c. but about a dozen (for they were but eleven, as he ſaith <hi>page the</hi> 30.) And it's not unlikely, they repreſented it thus falſly, that they might with leſs prick of Conſcience deny it.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:29497:14"/>2dly. It doth not follow, There were no ſuch Paper, becauſe theſe three men do not know of it. For, 1. it was ſeven years ago, and they might forget that which our Author remembred. 2. I am informed that <hi>Martyn</hi> did not at that time live at <hi>Hartford,</hi> and was not then ſo known in that place as he pretends to be now: and perhaps <hi>Lucas</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, however his buſineſs abroad might well enough hinder him from ſeeing and knowing of that which others, that were more at home or in Priſon, did both ſee and know: And the like may be ſaid for <hi>Stout.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3dly. Why did not <hi>Rich. Thomas</hi> alſo teſtifie as much as theſe men? for he both lived at <hi>Hartford</hi> then, and at <hi>London</hi> now. And why did they not ſend to <hi>Hartford,</hi> and have the teſtimony of the moſt part of the known <hi>Quakers</hi> of that time? But theſe men muſt be choſen out, whoſe teſtimony be it true or falſe, doth not at all determine the matter in queſtion.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly. That there was ſuch a Paper, that ſuch was the Contents of it; that it was ſigned by Eleven of the great Ones or Elders, is ſo far from being 3 great and manifeſt Lyes, that they are three great and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Truths: For the <hi>Bookſeller</hi> will produce it upon any juſt occaſion. Neither is the 4th particular a lye, viz. that it was diſliked: For <hi>G. Biſhope</hi> then of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoll</hi> wrote a large Letter in diſlike of it, which the Bookſeller can alſo produce: and if thoſe things were ſo, it's no great marvel if our Author remember them. So that if there was any miſtake in his relating this matter; 'twas onely of <hi>Hartford</hi> for <hi>Briſtoll;</hi> and this the <hi>Quakers</hi> at <hi>London;</hi> and particularly <hi>Alex. Parker, Geo. Whitehead, Stephen Criſp, &amp;c.</hi> whoſe names are to the Paper, How could they poſſibly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:29497:15"/>
be ignorant of it? yet notwithſtanding,<note n="*" place="margin">What's become of John Osgood's integrity, that he ſhould put his name among ſuch men as theſe?</note> they have the confidence to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the world with a ſeeming denial of the whole matter. But yet there's no reaſon to imagin that the Author was miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, either in that, for the title of the Letter is this: <hi>A Teſtimony from the Brethren, who were met together at London in the third month</hi> 1666. <hi>to be communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the faithful Friends and Elders in the Countries, by them to be read in their ſeveral meetings, and kept as a Teſtimony among them.</hi> Shall we think now that this Letter thus deſigned for the Countries and their ſeveral Meetings, thus authoriz'd by eleven great El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and ſent to <hi>Briſtol</hi> 90 miles from <hi>London,</hi> ſhall we think (I ſay) that it was not ſent to <hi>Hartford</hi> diſtant 20 miles? Believe it that will! Perhaps in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it might meet with oppoſition from the perſons to whoſe hands it firſt came (and that there is ſome cauſe to believe) and ſo might not be communicated to the whole People. But perhaps they take occaſion from ſome miſtaken word in our Authors relation of the Contents, to vilifie and deny the whole. [And indeed I hear that even <hi>H. Stout</hi> being rebuk'd for denying, confeſt the Paper; but ſaid, It was not to that intent as the Author relates] For our Author has told us (p. 22, 23.) and they deny it not, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>to cover the whoredoms of the wanton Miniſtry &amp;c. and unclean Strumpets,</hi> they <hi>did judg openly the miſtake of a Perſon, when the actions were true, and in the ſame houſe.</hi> It ſeems the Relators did truly inform of the man and actions, but miſtook the woman of the houſe for the ſervant, and therefore the teſtimony was
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29497:15"/>
made invalid, the criminals go free, and the poor witneſs condemn'd. O innocent, holy, and harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs People!</p>
            <p>So I could tell you the eminent <hi>Quakers</hi> name, who to a ſcrupulous man did ſeem to juſtify one of his Brethren in denying to know what he very well knew (when queſtioned by a Magiſtrate,) by this; <hi>he could not tell, becauſe he would not tell;</hi> and he ſaid it was uſual for friends ſo to do: but who would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, that even the Body of the <hi>Quakers</hi> in the Paper called, <hi>A Declaration from the People of God cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Quakers</hi> (relating to the Act againſt Conventicles) have theſe words? <hi>And as for the word, [diſloyal to the King] we have always paid our Taxes, and Aſſeſſments, and other dues and duties, more than any people, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our abilities;</hi> when their Neighbours all over <hi>England</hi> know there are (at leaſt) ſome Taxes or Aſſeſſments, which they have peremptorily refuſed; which thing being objected to <hi>G. Fox,</hi> (who with <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> (they ſay) was the Author of that Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,) he anſwer'd, We pay Our Taxes &amp;c. inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating that the term <hi>Our</hi> was not to be extended to the Taxes &amp;c. requir'd, but to thoſe paid. O wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful equivocation! But when a honeſt-harted woman told him, ſhe paid no Taxes &amp;c. he reply'd, Thy ſalt, and oyl, and vineger in the ſhop do all pay taxes; or to that purpoſe. Behold here the Doctrine and practice of this <hi>true Prophet whom John ſaid he was not!</hi> Behold the Anointed, <hi>whoſe Kingdom is eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in peace!</hi> has come up to the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> already, and how far he will excell them, we know not. But let's return to our Author. The ſubſtance of that Letter, whereof I have given you the title, is this; Theſe Eleven Brethren and Elders, viz. <hi>Rich. Farnſworth,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29497:16"/>
Alex. Parker, George Whitehead, Joſiah Coale, John Whitehead, Thomas Loc, Stephen Criſp, Tho. Green, John Moon, Tho. Briggs, James Parks,</hi> do by the operation of the Spirit of Truth conſider that their Society and Government cannot be kept inviolable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their covert enemies [by whom they mean the Hat-men] who are not afraid to ſpeak evil of Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nityes [<hi>G. Fox</hi> and his Adherents] and deſpiſe Government; they therefore do unanimouſly and with the Lords preſence (as they ſay) teſtifie (1) that ſuch as exalt themſelves above the Body of good and ancient Friends <hi>[G. Fox &amp;c.]</hi> ought not to have any dominion, office or rule in the Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That ſuch as are not in unity with the Miniſtry and Body have no Goſpel-Authority to be Judges in the Church, and their judgment ought not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded: that it is abominable pride when any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular will not admit of the judgment of the witneſs of God in Friends [<hi>G. Fox's</hi> and their opinion] to take place againſt him; for he, that is not juſtified by that, is condemned in himſelf and harden'd, [a noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Heretick.]</p>
            <p n="3">3. They teſtifie in the name of the Lord, that the Church has power (without the aſſent of diſſenters) to determine Controverſies, and that ſuch Perſons as will not ſubmit to their judgment conſiſtent with the Doctrine of antient Friends [that is, of <hi>G. Fox</hi> and his Party] but oppoſe it as the judgment of man, ought to be rejected, together with thoſe that counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and encourage them. They are joyned in one with Heathens and Infidels.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That ſuch diſapproved Miniſters ought (what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have been their gifts) to leave off miniſtring till they are reconciled to the Church: and if approved
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:29497:16"/>
perſons degenerate to diviſion, and countenance fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction [that is, the Hat-men] the Church has autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to deal with them in the ſame manner; to which if they ſubmit not, warning ought to be given in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral-Meetings to beware of them, and to have no fellowſhip with them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They warn and charge all Friends, that they have no hand in publiſhing the Books or Writings of ſuch as are not of unity with the Body; —and <hi>we farther deſire that from time to time faithfull and ſound Friends and Brethren [G. Fox</hi> and his Party] <hi>may have the view of ſuch things as are printed upon Truths account (as formerly it hath uſed to be) before they go to the Preſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. They adviſe that ſuch as are made Overſeers of the ſlock of God by the Holy-Spirit —admit not the weak to that truſt; and that none be admitted to order publick buſineſs, but thoſe that ſeek the good of all [that is, ſubmit to the great Body of <hi>G. Fox</hi> and his party]. They conclude thus: So, dear Friends, believing that you will be one with us —againſt thoſe who would limit the Lord to ſpeak without Inſtruments [that is, will obey the Light in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and not be ſubject to the dictates of <hi>G. Fox</hi> and his party] — and reject the counſel of the wiſe men, and the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of the<note n="*" place="margin">For they perceived many of their hearers, wearied and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with their long preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings &amp;c. would have had them to return home to their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments and Callings; but the proud way of living they had betaken themſelves to, they were not willing to leave, and therfore ſtrengthen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in it by ſevere Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</note> Prophets which gethered you, and would not allow him liberty in and by his Servants to appoint time and place wherein to meet — and call this
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29497:17"/>
Formal, and the Meetings of Man, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Now let all conſidering men judg, whether ever ſuch an arrogant, imperious and audacious Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per was given out by ſuch a number of Mortals! The Pope hath never (I think) taken ſo much power to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as to determin matters of this nature and in this manner, but in a General Council, and with their concurrence: but herein theſe men tranſcend him, and all that ever went before them: <hi>That they did owne thoſe men to whom they wrote, to be led and guided, and that they ought in all ſuch matters to be led and guided immediately by the infallible Spirit of God; and they did owne that thoſe againſt whom they wrote had been led and guided by the ſame infallible Spirit, and gave at this time no other evidence of their not being now led by it, but only their diſſent from theſe men in the matters mentioned:</hi> the cheif whereof in particular was, The not putting off the Hat to their prayers; which things conſidered, their giving Charges and Laws in the Name of the Lord to the perſons aforeſaid, is nothing leſs than arrogating a Spiritual and Divine Power over that which they teach, ought to be heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to as the Infallible and Divine Spirit, and that in thoſe matters which ſome of themſelves have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged might be otherwiſe ordered by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-Spirit of God. As <hi>John Whitehead</hi> (who is one of them) in the matter of the Hat, in the Paper fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned; and <hi>Geo. Whitehead</hi> in that other Paper ſent to <hi>J. Perrot:</hi> And did they not own <hi>John Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rot</hi> for a true Friend? and that he was ſent of God according to their Principles to preach at <hi>Rome?</hi> and did they not own his Sufferings there to be for the Truth? and <hi>Perrot</hi> ſayes in his Paper, <hi>I have received by expreſs commandment from the Lord God of Heaven
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:29497:17"/>
in the day of my Captivity in</hi> Rome, viz. <hi>to bear a ſure Teſtimony againſt the Cuſtom and Traditions of the taking off of the Hat by men, when they go to pray to God, the which they never had by Commandment from God:</hi> To this agrees what <hi>G. Fox</hi> ſaith in the Book of <hi>True-honour &amp;c.</hi> aforementioned, where he calls <hi>Worſhip with the Hat voluntary Humility and not of command by Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</hi> And muſt now this Revelation to this eminent Prophet and Sufferer given him in his Captivity be deſpiſed and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for a deluſion, becauſe it is not approv'd by <hi>George Fox?</hi> muſt the apprehenſion of Scandal bear ſway againſt ſuch a Revelation, amongſt thoſe People, whoſe practice is full of Scandals, and liked the better by them on the account of diſtinguiſhing them from others? Is it not evident enough that the true reaſon of their not receiving his teſtimony was, its contradiction to the practice of <hi>G. Fox?</hi> had it been reveal'd to him firſt, it had been receiv'd readily; but now it muſt be rejected. Here we may perceive clearly, what it is that influences theſe men in the owning or diſowning of Divine Revelations: however there's no gainſaying, but <hi>that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the advantages that any Ruling Quaker has, he may be groſsly deluded, and take that for an infallible Revelation from God, which proceeds indeed from the ſpirit of deceit.</hi> For thus <hi>Fox</hi> and his party ſay, <hi>Perrot</hi> and his party did; and the like might <hi>Perrot</hi> ſay of <hi>Fox:</hi> And <hi>Fox</hi> or his party cannot give any the leaſt ſolid ground, whereby to decide the Controverſie between them. Therefore we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude juſtly that theſe men, as Rulers and Prophets, are led by a Self-contradicting, Proud, Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and Tyrannical Spirit. For they equally
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29497:18"/>
pretend Revelation, and if there be any advantage in this matter, it is on <hi>Perrot's</hi> ſide and not on <hi>Fox's;</hi> ſo that if <hi>Perrot</hi> be condemned, <hi>Fox</hi> cannot ſtand. That he doth ſtand among the greater number of <hi>Quakers,</hi> proceeds meerly from his Intereſt, Cunning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And as the whole party of the Hat-men is to be oppoſed to the whole party of <hi>Foxonians;</hi> ſo in particular <hi>George Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Briſtol</hi> is to be oppoſed to every one of thoſe eleven Miniſters; for he was ſo far from atteſting to their Teſtimony (as every Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, had it been true, ought to have done) that he contradicted it, and wrote a large Letter in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to it; The ſubſtance of which is this, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Having conſidered their Paper in the Spirit of Truth, he is moved of the Lord to let them know, 1. That it is much, that they ſo few, ſo young, and ſo very little in compariſon of the Body, or thoſe whom they count Elders, ſhould take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to determine in things of ſo high a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which if they are to be done, ought to be done by the full conſent of thoſe who are in Authority in the Church (if ſo be there be ſuch an Authority ſo to determine) and not by a few, and thoſe not at all deputed in the thing. If you ſay (ſaith he) you have not determined ſo as to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon the Body of Friends, but only given your own judgment in the thing: I anſwer, you are very poſitive and plain in the determination.</q> [And ſo repeating their Preface, he collects]—<q>which is in the nature of a Civil Commandment.</q> [Then he recites their firſt particular, and ſayes]—<q>which is as much as an Inſtitution.</q> [Then of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Particular he ſaith]—<q>which is an Inhibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</q> [Of the third Particular he ſaith]—<q>which
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:29497:18"/>
is Doctrine.</q> [Of the fourth he ſaith]—<q>which is Correction.</q> [Of the fifth]—<q>which is Admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</q> [Of the ſixth]—<q>which is Exhortation.</q> [Of the Concluſion he ſaith] —<q>this is Inſtruction.</q> Next he ſaith, <q>The Spirit of the Lord in this day, and in the days of the Apoſtles bears not the ſame proportion: then were Apoſtles, Paſtors, Teachers, Elders, &amp;c. but in this day the Spirit it ſelf is Paſtor, Teacher, Elder, &amp;c. ſo that if the Spirit move any to declare or ſpeak, that is the Apoſtle, Teacher, Elder, &amp;c. So that we have not now things in the diſpoſition of Perſons, but according to the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer which moves in everyone, ſo there is not that Hazard, as to Apoſtacy, as was in that day — ſo I know no Paſtor, Teacher, Elder, &amp;c. but as I find moving in any to any of theſe things; and that, which would be otherwiſe than this, leaps into Apoſtacy, and will ſeek to bring in dark night a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and will be ſecluding the thing to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and not the perſon to the thing: and as for my part, if that day ſhould prevaile, or theſe things which your Paper ſemes to hold forth and inforce, I have no other expectation, but that the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe we ſhall receive at your hands — as we together received from the hands of thoſe who would have held us in Captivity. 3. The Seed is come in which the Miniſtry is to end. Now for you, becauſe you Miniſtred, to think to ſettle your ſelves in the place of the Heir, and to inforce your ſtation,—is not to allow that the Seed is come; and whether your Paper doth not ſo ſpeak, view it over again, and let that which ſhould, judge in the matter. — Friends and Brethren, take heed how you ſet up your Laws and Conſtitutions
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:29497:19"/>
over his dominion — many have attempted it, and have been broken to pieces; and if you do the ſame, the ſame will be your portion from the hand of the Lord. In the Power you are ſafe, but when once you go to outward things to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve your ſtation, and keep you up, as Papers, ſtrivings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you err ſo much from the Power, and this will work you down alſo, if you oppoſe your ſelves againſt his Kingdom. <hi>Briſtol the</hi> 3d <hi>of the</hi> 11 <hi>month,</hi> 1666.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Here we have the infallible Spirit of the Quakers in <hi>G. Bi hop</hi> giving judgment againſt the eleven El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, that they had gone from their Principle into the way of Apoſtacy, and propheſying their down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal. And he that knew <hi>George Biſhop,</hi> or has read his writings, will (I think) find reaſon enough to take his judgment concerning their principles, as ſoon as any or all of the eleven Elders. So that they have not only offer'd this affront to mankind, <hi>viz. That they profeſs in Principles and Practices neceſſary to man's happineſs, to diſtinguiſh themſelves from all other men, and for the truth and certainty of thoſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and practices, they bring no evidence, but the inward Teſtimony of the Light in every man, and yet condemn all men as unfaithful to that Light, (how innocent ſoever in their own Conſciences) that are contrary to them, or agree not with them:</hi> which is in effect, to give the lie to every man beſides them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to ſay, that all the World, except <hi>Quakers,</hi> are lyers; And the thing is true in reſpect of primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtianity, (which they pretend to) that it brought ſuch evidence with it to them, to whom it was fully preach'd, that no conſiderate man would
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:29497:19"/>
disbelieve it, but he muſt be a lyer, and wilfully blind. But theſe men do not only thus affront all mankind that conſent not to them, but alſo they conclude, even all Quakers, (that agree with them in all their Principles and Practices wherein they differ from others) to be ſelf-condemn'd, if they ſubject not themſelves to their Judgment in ſo ſmall a matter as is the covering or uncovering the Head when others pray, and things of that kind. For I never heard that any Hat-man kept on his Hat when himſelf prayed, except <hi>Perrot.</hi> And ſo they contradict in the Name of the Lord, that very voice in men, which they have taught them to give heed to as the voice of the Lord. So when <hi>J. Pennyman</hi> carrying all his Books to a Friend of his near the Exchange, was mov'd to burn ſome waſte papers there in his paſſage, pouring out ſome Quakers Books, which (he having a little before born Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to <hi>G. Fox</hi> and <hi>Whithead's</hi> face, againſt their deceitful Declaration, and another Scurrilous Paper) they were ſo offended at him for, that <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> next day in a Letter to <hi>J. P.</hi> calls this his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking to burn <hi>their Books</hi> [not a word of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as is in their printed Paper, to take with the People] <hi>a mad and wicked action, to which the Devil inſtigated and led him.</hi> Which Letter he order'd <hi>G. L.</hi> to get from him; afterward when <hi>J. P.</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd of the wrong he had in having the Letter ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from him ſurreptitiouſly; <hi>G. Whithead</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, that he was moved of the Lord to ſend it, and underſtanding that it was not receiv'd in the ſame love in which it was ſent, he was alſo moved of the Lord to ſend for it again: to which <hi>J. Penny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> reply'd, that he had neither opened nor read
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:29497:20"/>
that Letter nor knew from whom it came, till the ſaid <hi>G. L.</hi> came and asked him concerning it. Thus we ſee that <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> could pretend a motion from the Lord, not only to condemn with deteſtation what his Friend was mov'd to, but alſo to ſend one to get away that which was become another mans proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and that upon a falſe ſuggeſtion. Moreover, <hi>G. W.</hi> ſaid, <hi>he would not return it, except the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd him: What ſtrange Doctrine is this</hi> (replied J. P.) <hi>that thou wilt not return me that which was ſtolen from me, except the Lord require thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">XVI. Moreover, let thoſe that have been careful to compare the judgment of the Ruling Elders with the Truth, (in thoſe things that might by future events be diſcerned) tel us whether particular perſons or the Juncto has been more deceived. God in his Providence did (as has been commonly related) for ends beſt known to himſelf, raiſe up among the <hi>Quakers</hi> a man (by name <hi>Thomas Ebbit</hi>) who came out of <hi>Huntington-ſhire</hi> to <hi>London</hi> in great haſte to Propheſie the burning of the City, and arrived here a day or two before that dreadful Fire began: This Man (as I am informed) the Elders, who ſo highly pretend to the diſcerning of Spirits, took unto them, and examin'd him concerning it, and inſtead of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving his Propheſie, they did almoſt perſwade the Man that it was a Deluſion; and ſo in a matter that ſo highly concerned them as well as others, I never could hear that any of them gave credit to him, but were as far from diſcerning Truth in that Word which came to paſs, as any of their Neighbors; and ſuffered equally with them in that general Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity. And ſo this Prophet, who, if they had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven heed to him, might have been a great glory to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:29497:20"/>
their party, is the ſhame and reproach of them all to whom his Tidings came, but eſpecially to the Judging Elders. Suppoſing now <hi>G. F.</hi> and his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents to be the old Prophets (as they would be eſtemed) we ſee by this inſtance, they can contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict the Word of the Lord in the younger Prophets, as did the old Prophet, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 13. But me-thinks the ſad fate of that young Prophet, for giving heed to the old one, ſhould ſufficiently caution the young Quakers againſt believing the old ones contrary to the Light in their own particulars.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. Having now ſeen <hi>G. Fox's</hi> forgery in the Name of the Lord, and the Elders contradicting the Elders in the ſame Meeting in the Name of the Lord, and the whole Body of <hi>Quakers</hi> divided in the Name of the Lord between the <hi>Foxonians</hi> and the Hat-men; and <hi>G. Biſhop</hi> by the ſame Spirit oppoſing the Eleven Miniſters; Let us now take a view of <hi>Jo. Swinton</hi> oppoſing himſelf in the Name of the Lord. And whereas he ſaith (p. 22.) in extenuation of his fault, in writing that Paper which he is charged with in the Spirit of the Hat p. 34. that <hi>ſoon after he was convinc't</hi> [to be a <hi>Quaker] he was ſhut up in a cloſe priſon, and continued a priſoner for divers years, and being at a diſtance and much alone — was betrayed to the writing of that Paper mentioned, and when he came to ſee what he had done by it, he came forth in abſolute judgment againſt that Paper, and the Spirit in which it was writ, and this judgment was not in an hour of Temptation, &amp;c.</hi> So he acknowledges the Truth of what our Author has told concerning him, but he deny's the inference, namely that his Recantation was rather in an hour of Temptation.</p>
            <p>If it be true (as true it is) that this recanted Paper
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:29497:21"/>
was wrote in <hi>Newgate</hi> 1664; then we may juſtly complain that this man (who has ſometimes born a great place and title) comes far ſhort of that ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that might be expected from him; for <hi>Newgate</hi> was far enough from being a cloſe priſon, there being very many of the <hi>Quakers</hi> priſoners with him at the ſame time; alſo I find him come to that proficiency in <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> in the year 1660, that he undertakes to write a Paper directed <hi>To all the Friends to Truth in the Nations:</hi> and he begins thus, <hi>Dear Friends, I am commanded of the Lord God, &amp;c</hi> and in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, <hi>I ſpeak what in the Infallible I ſee and know.</hi> This (they ſay) was written from the <hi>Gatehouſe</hi>-Priſon: here he tels them, <hi>the enemy hath entred, and I ſay (in the dread &amp; Authority and Power of the Living God) hath leavened many and the Seed hath been and is bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened in many particulars, and in one another; The world hath entred, Self hath entred, the high mind hath entred, &amp;c.</hi> In the year 1664, I find another Paper of his, written at <hi>Franly</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire</hi> the 27th of the 6th month: And the Recanted Paper called a<note n="*" place="margin">Therein he writes thus; For Friends in the Name and Authority of the Living and Eternal God — I have ſeen the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and Fury, the Indignation of the Almighty God ready to break forth into a mighty flame, — yea, and the Leaders, many of them not ſtanding clear herein: <hi>[ſpeaking of outward things]</hi> Is this all? Nay, nay! <hi>Iſrael's</hi> wound lies deeper, is more Spiritual and inward, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the more incurable: Pride, Conceited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, High-mindedneſs, love of Dominion, Selfiſhneſs, an Exalted ſpirit, an Itching mind, to declare words in and above the Seed of the Kingdom, hath deeply entred Iſrael, yea the Leaders, the Leaders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> bears date the third of the ninth Month, which was about ten weeks after: Let the Reader judg, whether his being a cloſe Priſoner,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:29497:21"/>
and much alone, and at diſtance, be a righteous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe: it's obſervable that in this time of Temptation (as he now calls it) he wrote that which is as likely to have been prophetical as any thing he ever wrote; for in the beginning of the great Sickneſs, which we know was followed by the Fire, he ſaith thus: <hi>O London, London! thy Tryals are but beginning; Theſe are but the beginnings of the evils that are to overtake thee; Deſolation, Deſolation ſhall enter into thy Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels, yea even into thy very bowels!</hi> 29th <hi>of the month called</hi> July, 1665. Afterward in the year 1668. I find a Paper of his dated 26th of the 6th month, directed to the Mens Meeting, wherein he tells of his coming to <hi>London</hi> the Winter foregoing, and of the conſtructions put upon his 64th Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which (ſaith he) <hi>was writ in the expreſs mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, and in his manifeſt leadings out of and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all thoughts and reaſonings,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and that upon every recourſe to God, the ſearcher of his heart in that matter, he had always renewed juſtification and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation;</hi> Then he gives an account of what paſſed between him and them at a Meeting with the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, how they judged his Paper in the Name of the Lord, and would have him to aquieſce in their judgment; that being in his own hired Houſe, it roſe in him to viſit Friends in <hi>London</hi> again; that the Lord was with him as he paſſed in <hi>Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Biſhoprick, Yorkſhire, Lincolnſhire, Norfolk, Suffolk, Eſſex.</hi> And he concludes thus: <hi>which Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per I am again to acquaint you ſtands juſtified in every tittle of it, and I am plainly to acquaint you, that I cannot retract it, nor the leaſt ſyllable of it; God doth juſtifie me in it, and I ſhould be Rebellious and Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to my Light and Life, if I ſhould retract it or
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:29497:22"/>
any ſyllable of it, or deny the Spirit in which it was writ,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now after all this he retracts it, and denyes the Spirit in which it was writ; whereupon I would ask him; What greater evidence has he of the Spirit of the Lord in his Retractation, than he had in his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion? However doth he not herein plainly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that the Spirit of Truth and Light, by which he did profeſs to be led and guided for four or five years together, was the ſpirit of Error and Darkneſs? and that the <hi>Quakers</hi> (notwithſtanding their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to Infallibility) are upon their preſent princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples incident to Blaſphemy, and that for a long time together? And whether this kind of Blaſphemy be not a deadly ſin? or whether a man may live in it a long time and be in the Favour of God all the while? If <hi>John Swinton</hi> can ſatisfie himſelf in his Retractation, let him not be ſo vain to imagine that he can ſatisfie others that require a reaſon of what they hold. It he would take as much pains with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf now as he pretends to have done heretofore, I am perſwaded he might ſee, that the worldly glory of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and conſequently of himſelf, is the great Argument that ſways with him in his Recantation, for <hi>the Child muſt not be divided, nor the Seemleſs Garment rent.</hi> How great is the modeſty of our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, that only <hi>appeals to the impartial</hi> in this caſe, <hi>whether this Recantation was not done rather in an hour of Temptation;</hi> and doth not aſſert it abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, having ſuch ſtrong Arguments for ſo doing? But how great the immodeſty of <hi>W. Pen,</hi> to charge that for a Lye, of which himſelf can have but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectural knowledge. But what wonder? ſince he ſeems by his late Pamphlets to have abandon'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:29497:22"/>
to be <hi>G. Fox's</hi> and the <hi>Quakers</hi> Hector. There was a complaint againſt him of divers Lies, Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and other abuſes committed by him in his Book intituled, <hi>The Spirit of Truth,</hi> &amp;c. carried to the <hi>Bull and Mouth</hi> to be exhibited to the Body of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> or Mens Meeting, then ſitting there, by about half a ſcore Citizens and others; but they were not admitted — <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> told them, he would ſhew it to <hi>W. Pen,</hi> if they would ſet their hands to it. It ſeems he that comes to King <hi>G. Fox's</hi> Court muſt obſerve the formalities of that Court, and though this complaint has been long in <hi>Stephen Criſp's</hi> hands ſigned according to order, yet no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is return'd, but that he had ſhew'd it to <hi>W. Pen,</hi> and <hi>W. P.</hi> had anſwer'd it in Print; indeed <hi>W. P.</hi> in his <hi>Winding-ſheet,</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Anabaptiſts came to the</hi> Bull and Mouth <hi>to demand judgment againſt</hi> W. P. <hi>about All, for Many, were they not well imploy'd?</hi> What <hi>Pen!</hi> is this the cuſtom of <hi>G. Fox's</hi> Court to jeer the poor Petitioners? to reject their complaint with Scorn, and belie them to boot? For the complaint conſiſted of at leaſt ſixteen particulars, whereof All for Many was but one. The Truth is, I do not ſee how <hi>W. P.</hi> can vindicate himſelf from the Nature and Dignity of a Knight of the Poſt, and conſequently the Title will be his due. Provided always that it be taken for the proper character of a Knight of the Poſt, that he is one that frequently and publickly aſſerts by Oath, that which he either knows to be falſe, or doth not know to be true: And that <hi>G. P's</hi> word publickly given, may (according to the <hi>Quakers</hi> Principle) be taken to have the force (and the falſity in that caſe to deſerve the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) of an Oath. Beſides that his frequent appeals
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:29497:23"/>
to God and calling him to witneſs and judge, have the true nature of Oaths, and are ſo eſteem'd by all ſober and intelligent men. Wherefore ſince <hi>W. Pen</hi> loves not that we ſhould call him bare <hi>William,</hi> as the <hi>Quakers</hi> do, but doth almoſt beg his due title of <hi>J. Morſe</hi> (ſee <hi>Plain dealing, p.</hi> 7.) I think it but equal that we call him Mr. <hi>P n.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">XVIII In the next place let us look upon <hi>William Goſnell's</hi> Teſtimony, which in two pages contains ſo much virulent and opprobious language, that I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude it could not proceed from ſuch a Novice-writer as <hi>W. G.</hi> It looks more like the work of an older proficient in that manner of ſpeaking, and may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree better to <hi>G. W.</hi> than to <hi>W. G.</hi> and that which further induces me to think ſo, is, that the man inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the <hi>Spirit of the Hat</hi> his name (as I am inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) is not written <hi>Goſnel</hi> as in the Spirit of <hi>Alex.</hi> but <hi>Goſnold;</hi> but whether that be ſo or no, it's not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſuall with the <hi>Quakers</hi> to give as much credit to one another as is the ſetting their Names to things they know not. Thus <hi>William Sparrow</hi> deſired <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Trevers</hi> and <hi>John Pennyman</hi> to ſign a certificate (of the contents whereof they knew not the truth or falſity) becauſe it was drawn up and approved by <hi>G. Fox, Rich. Hubberthorn, &amp;c.</hi> which <hi>J. P.</hi> refuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Sparrow</hi> was offended at him; and he received a check from <hi>G. Fox,</hi> for adviſing him to caution Friends not to ſubſcribe any thing they were igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of, through the eſteem and great confidence they had of his mind to have it ſo, <hi>for</hi> (ſaid <hi>J. P.) if they think i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be thy mind to have it done, they will do it, tho' they be ignorant of it themſelves;</hi> to which <hi>Reb. Trevers</hi> (a great Propheteſs among them) agreed, ſaying moreover, <hi>that if ſhe had a motion from
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:29497:23"/>
the Lord as ſhe believed, yet if he (G. Fox) did not owne it ſo to be, ſhe ſhould deny it.</hi> She further ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>that her Maid ſhould ſay, Jo. Pennyman was a wiſe man, and would not ſubſcribe that Paper, elſe ſhe believed her Maſter would have done it.</hi> This refuſall was ſo much reſented by another of their then chief Miniſters, that he told <hi>J. P.</hi> that if he had ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the ſaid Certificate, he would have ſtood betwixt God and him in ſo doing, alleaging that it was their practice in ſuch caſes; yea his and their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity againſt <hi>J. Pennyman, J. Osgood</hi> and others (in theſe days, being about 11 or 12 years ſince) that oppoſ'd the irregularities of the 2d dayes Meeting, was ſo great, he called them a company of baſe fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low's. Theſe things conſidered, no marvel if <hi>W. G.</hi> might not give <hi>G. W.</hi> leave to write what he would, and ſet his name to't</p>
            <p>But 3dly, when I firſt ſaw <hi>Goſnel's</hi> name in the <hi>Spirit of Alexander,</hi> I expected nothing leſs than a denyal of what is related to have been ſaid by <hi>G. F.</hi> (Spirit of the Hat, p. 27.) viz. <hi>Friends, al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ho I have not told it you, I do now declare it, I have Power to bind and to looſe whom I pleaſe:</hi> but it ſeems it was true, and how can it be otherwiſe, that ſo great a King and Prophet as <hi>G. Fox</hi> ſhould not have ſuch a Power? However this <hi>Goſnel</hi> confeſſes to have ſpoken unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedly, when he reflected upon the zeal of that man of God, though he had ſaid (as I have heard) when he was deſired to go to <hi>G. F.</hi> to be reconciled, &amp;c. <hi>I abhor to proſtrate my Reputation at the Feet of any Mortal:</hi> yet before his laſt g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng beyond ſea, did comply with him, and is now become a Preacher a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them.</p>
            <p>But let us ſee what it was that provoked King
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:29497:24"/>
               <hi>George's</hi> zeal to ſuch a height, which occaſion'd <hi>W.G.</hi> to think he would have ſtruck <hi>S. Newton!</hi> I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand there was of late a Meeting ſet up by <hi>G. F.</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Account of the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſufferings, whence as occaſion ſerved they had recourſe to the Lawyers for their adviſe to elude the proceedings of their Proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors. At one of theſe Meetings <hi>S. N.</hi> produced <hi>G. Fox's</hi> Book to the Judges and Lawyers againſt their proceedings, by which he told them they made void the blood of all thoſe that have ſuffered for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake in thoſe matters; and alſo diſliked their making uſe of a <hi>Quaker</hi> as their Solicitor, who was under an ill fame, (ſee Spirit of Hat p. 42.) but fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd by <hi>G. Fox:</hi> theſe things ſo tranſported their chief Prophet, that <hi>W. G.</hi> thought by his poſtures and carriage, he would have ſtruck <hi>S. N.</hi> who more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over produced a Letter from <hi>Rob. Duncomb</hi> and <hi>John Jennocks,</hi> relating the Death of one <hi>Rich. White,</hi> who for following their Solicitors adviſe in theſe matters (conſidering the Doctrine and Practice of <hi>G. Fox</hi> himſelf and the <hi>Quakers</hi>) had upon his death-bed been much wounded in Spirit, and deſired <hi>R. D.</hi> to warn Friends how they <hi>went down to Egypt for help,</hi> or went from the Light in themſelves to follow the advice of men. Had not <hi>G. F.</hi> the man of God think ye, reaſon enough to be in a fury at ſuch a bold man as this <hi>S. Newton,</hi> who durſt thus ſhew him his palpable contradiction to himſelf, and the ſad conſequence thereof?</p>
            <p>Well, But <hi>Goſnel</hi> (what ever becomes of himſelf) will needs have our Author (among many other great wickedneſſes) to have brought forth <hi>a Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous work, to be irreligious and void both of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Spirit:</hi> Why ſo I pray. Why? becauſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:29497:24"/>
in one place he pleads <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Goſpel-Liberty,</hi> [that is, He will not count himſelf oblig'd to keep off his Hat by vertue of <hi>George's</hi> Law, finding no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward obligation of conſcience ſo to do:] but in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place he ſayth, <hi>He keeps it neither off nor on upon a Religious Account,</hi> tho' the <hi>Foxonians</hi> keep it off upon ſuch an account. This is the monſtrous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction found out by this accurate Diſtinguiſher, who if he cannot find a knot in the Bulruſh will be ſure to make one. Why doth he not alſo charge the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> with the like contradiction, for bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Chriſtians, <hi>ſtand faſt in the Liberty of Chriſt,</hi> and yet ſaying that <hi>he that regards not the day to the Lord, he doth not regard it?</hi> ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.9. and ſome made <hi>Conſcience of eating,</hi> &amp;c. and others eat, <hi>asking no queſtion for Conſcience ſake.</hi> Can a man ſtand faſt in the liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made him free, and not upon a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous account? or cat, or keep a day in aſſertion of that Liberty, and yet not upon a conſcientious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Chriſt's Liberty? And yet make no conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of eating or not eating, but uſe his liberty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in as others did not who abſtained for Conſcience-ſake? I knew a Religious man who always put off his Gloves when he went to Prayer, and no doubt but he did it out of Conſcience, but who of a thouſand did ſo beſides himſelf? And who would have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to it, had he impoſed that obſervance? but enough to this impertinent man.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. We come in the laſt place to conſider their vindication of their <hi>Miniſtry</hi> from being <hi>Vicious and Wanton; and that Strumpets are amongſt them. This</hi> W. P. <hi>doth in the Name of the holy God deny,</hi> p. 15. <hi>and defies any man on Earth to prove any part of this
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:29497:25"/>
ungodly charge — to ſo much as belongs to any one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon by us</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>accounted of it.</hi> And <hi>John Boulton</hi> and <hi>Samuel Newton declare in the uprightneſs of their hearts that they know of no ſuch, nor can acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge any ſuch to be either of their Miniſtry or their Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Man would think now that theſe Men would not dare thus to appeal to God (which is the higheſt Teſtimony that Men can give) but that they know their Teſtimony to be very true, even infallible; and that our Author is a very wicked man in writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a charge againſt them. But have patience Reader, and hear what I ſay on the Authors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half.</p>
            <p>Foraſmuch as <hi>W. P.</hi> exclaims upon us for proof, and promiſeth that an hearing ſhall not be refuſed, we chalenge them to make choice of ſix diſintereſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, judicious, and honeſt perſons, ſuch as we may have no juſt and reaſonable exception againſt; and we on our part will make choice of the ſame number, and ſo qualified, againſt whom they ſhall have no juſt and reaſonable exception; to which twelve per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo agreed upon, we will referr the Judgment of this matter of Fact, and all other matters of Fact, wherein you have in your late Pamphlets ſo horrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cryed out of being belyed and ſlandered, and of the complaint afore-mentioned: and if in the Judgment of theſe twelve men we ſhall be found to have ſaid that in detraction from you, of which we cannot give a ſufficient reaſon, we will then give you ſuch ſatisfaction as theſe men ſhall agree upon; Provided that you alſo ingage your ſelves to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the like ſentence, if the falure be found in you. And leſt it ſhould fall our that we may not agree
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:29497:25"/>
in the choice of ſuch a number of Perſons, we are willing in caſe of difference about them, to refer the Umpirage to the Lord Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> or any <hi>Alderman</hi> on the Bench, or any one of Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Common-Council-men. If you accept theſe terms, ſignifie your mind in writing, and leave it with <hi>Francis Smith</hi> the Bookſeller, and you ſhall find Perſons ready to comply with you. If you do not accept them, I hope no conſiderate man will henceforth ever believe either your word or oath; for ſo I call your appeals to God, your imprecations and curſings.</p>
            <p>But that the Reader may not too much wonder at this ſtrange Confidence on both ſides, let him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that their loud denial doth but ſeem to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict our Author's charge; for he ſpeaks of the time paſt, and they of the time preſent when they wrote; whereby they exclude from being accounted of their Miniſtry, 1. Thoſe that have been found guilty and are diſowned, ſuch as <hi>J. C. D. B. W. W. T. T. T. M.</hi> and others. 2. Thoſe that have been guilty, but are deceaſed. 3. Thoſe that are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owned by theſe Perſons that write, tho' perhaps they may be owned by other Perſons or Meetings in the Country: For I ſuppoſe that <hi>John Bolton</hi> his keeping on his Hat when <hi>Tho. Salthouſe</hi> pray'd in the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (after he had committed the offence of being a Witneſs at <hi>John Oſgood's</hi> Wedding) was ſuch a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owning him that <hi>J. Bolton</hi> would in preſence of God have deny'd him to be of their Miniſtry; and yet at the ſame time he was owned by the multitude. 4. I doubt they exclude alſo thoſe that have ſinned and have been judged by <hi>G. F.</hi> or ſome few, and have own'd their condemnation, and ſo have been par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:29497:26"/>
For I hear there is one <hi>W. C.</hi> in <hi>New-England</hi> who was long ago accuſed here in <hi>London,</hi> but either denyed the charge, or through favour or otherwiſe avoided ſentence: but now <hi>G. Fox</hi> writes from <hi>New-England</hi> that <hi>W. C.</hi> ownes condemnation. 5. If any error has been found in the evidence, as in the caſe of <hi>Tho. Mur.</hi> who <hi>under pretence of Phyſick or Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgery, made it his common practice to commit Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, and was employed by G. Fox to judg Perſons and Meetings, &amp;c.</hi> (See Spirit of Hat, p. 31.) Here the miſtake of the Miſtreſs for the Maid (though the man was guilty) got him rather juſtification, and the reporters condemnation as aboveſaid. Now I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that in ſuch a caſe as this, ſuch a Miniſter will be deny'd by them to be guilty till further evidence appear; and when ſuch evidence that cannot be eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded doth appear, then he ſhall perhaps be judged and diſown'd privately, and ſo not of their Miniſtry. 6. The ſcandalous familiarity of the Prophets and Propheteſſes, or Miſtreſſes before marriage, muſt go for nothing, that is, muſt have no force to prove mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of viciouſneſs in their Miniſtry: Now this is the caſe of a great Man among them and his Lady, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning whom <hi>M. Y.</hi> informs <hi>that M. B<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. ſaid ſhe was grieved and burthen'd at her heart,</hi> by reaſon that <hi>M. B.</hi> her Brother had reprov'd ſome ſecreſies between thoſe two, fearing leſt they ſhould become publick to the World to diſhonour Truth.</p>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered, how wary are theſe men in their challenge? and how do they prevaricate with God and men in their appeal? Allow us the equity you deſire, let the <hi>Quakers</hi> Informations by word or writing be taken as proof upon Oath; and let the ſolemn Teſtimony of others have the force of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:29497:26"/>
ſolid Evidence; let thoſe that have declared and prayed amongſt you with tokens of Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, be accounted to have been, or to be of your Miniſtry, and then let us go to tryal. In the mean time let me tell you, we have ſeen, and could make publick the information of <hi>M. Y.</hi> wherein many of your Friends, and four or five of your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, were concern'd; and whereby their names would be ſufficiently expoſed; but it is ſo full of obſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and abominable prophaneneſs, that love to the profeſſion of Religion, and charity to the World, and Perſonal modeſty forbid its Publication. And we have ſeen in <hi>Andrew Robeſon's</hi> Anſwer to <hi>Jaſper Bat</hi> and <hi>John Graves</hi> Letter, (to <hi>John Swinton</hi>) theſe words; <hi>What was it in that Paper chiefly hath given you offence? was it the intimation that many of the Leaders of Iſrael are ſo inclin'd, and had a tend ncy to draw back into the fleſh-potts of Egypt again? which you call lyes</hi> and <hi>ſlanders: if ſuch things be lyes, what meanes theſe frequent and abominable Whoredoms that ſome are run into, &amp;c.</hi>— and in the cloſe he writes particularly to <hi>J. Gr.</hi> ſaying, <hi>How contrary is this thy work to the private diſcourſes betwixt thee and me, even now in London not a week before this, — were not thy very words, ALL OUR MINISTERS ARE WRONG, &amp;c.</hi> 18th <hi>of the</hi> 5th <hi>Month,</hi> 1668. And notwithſtanding <hi>John Bolton's</hi> ſeeming denyal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet he hath ſince acknowledged that he had by him the confeſſion of the two women chiefly concern'd in the ſaid information, whereof our Author has made mention p. 43. We could name ſeveral of your body, (notwithſtanding your impudent denyal of it) ſome that have had Meetings frequently at their houſes, and others, great ſufferers for your cauſe, that have
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:29497:27"/>
been detected of whoredom or uncleanneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>T. Rawl.</hi> for a long time <hi>G. Fox's</hi> companion, was at length detected of great wantonneſs toward the Maids. We may obſerve here that <hi>W. P.</hi> ſaith, <hi>an hearing againſt any of them ſhall never be refuſ'd:</hi> and that our Author doth wickedly diſtinguiſh, when he ſaith p. 29. <hi>If any of the Miniſters commit a fault, their Peers or Equals are only to be their Judges, and not the Laity.</hi> And yet that is ſo far true, that thoſe words, or to that effect, were ſpoken by famous <hi>S. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> upon occaſion of <hi>W. Mucklow's</hi> offering to be at the Hearing of <hi>John Whitehead</hi> upon an information of wantonneſs committed by him, concerning which <hi>W. M.</hi> could ſay ſomething, but was rejected for the reaſon aforeſaid. And <hi>John Harwood</hi> (formerly one of their Miniſters, and whilſt ſuch, found guilty of noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious uncleanneſs) falling our with <hi>G. Fox,</hi> accuſ'd him of divers matters; but could not obtain a Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and thereupon publiſh'd his charge in print. And when <hi>W. M.</hi> accuſ'd <hi>G. Fox</hi> to be a reſpecter of Perſons in judgment, tho' divers confeſſ'd the charge was true, yet none had the courage at the Meeting to take his part: but woes and curſes were pronounc'd againſt him by the Grandees, for accuſing an Elder. So, when (at an extraordinary Meeting after the great plague) <hi>E. Barns,</hi> as the Miniſters were exalting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, cry'd out while <hi>R. Farnſworth</hi> was preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>You have whored from the Lord. Farnſworth</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, Thou art a whore [or the whore]: whereupon <hi>M. Stanclift</hi> ſaid ſoftly, <hi>An unſavory word;</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> next ſecond-day Meeting, <hi>M. St.</hi> being greived i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Spirit, complain'd of the carriage of the ſaid Meeting where he expected humiliation rather than exalta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion: but they (in ſtead of hearkening to him) ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:29497:27"/>
notice of that word <hi>unſavoury,</hi> judged him, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt him out for that, as they ſaid in their Letter of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication (ſubſcribed by <hi>A. Stodart, T. Covency, J. Elſon, G. Laytee</hi>) he had called <hi>the Spirit of Truth an unſavoury Spirit.</hi> Thus was this man of known honeſty caſt out for appearing againſt the Miniſtry. But if you would have your Miniſtry fully vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as to this matter, provoke <hi>Mr. Hicks</hi> to give you the particulars of that general ſugeſtion of your vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, mentioned in the end of his <hi>Continuation, &amp;c.</hi> and then clear your ſelves of it if you can.</p>
            <p n="20">XX. Thus I have conſidered the Teſtimony which they ſeverally give of their own Innocency and the Innocency of their Body, which I know not what People in the world would have had the face to call them by that title except the <hi>Foxonians.</hi> Now becauſe I have in theſe Papers ſometimes uſed that denomination to thoſe people, and alſo called <hi>G. Fox</hi> by the title of <hi>King,</hi> tho the reaſon of theſe titles is evident enough to him that takes notice of <hi>J. Coals</hi> Letter, yet leſt to the unwary Reader I may be thought to have done this ſlightly, I will conſider his Teſtimony more fully. 1. The Letter comes from <hi>Joſiah Coal,</hi> a mighty man in their eſteem both in his Life and at his Death, for the Narrative of his Life and Death was Printed for his greater Glory. 2. This Letter was approved of, not only by <hi>G. Fox</hi> himſelf, but alſo by his Peers the Elders, among whom no doubt but it was read, and by their concurrence ordered to be Regiſtred among things worthy to be Recorded, and there put in the very firſt place, tho' it hath not the oldeſt date, or elſe why ſhould it be put there at all? It cannot be imagined that ſuch a thing could be done without the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:29497:28"/>
Elders their either explicit or implicit concurrence. So then what is attributed to <hi>G. Fox</hi> by <hi>J. C.</hi> is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by <hi>George</hi> himſelf, and the ſelect Elders at leaſt.</p>
            <p>As for the Contents of this Teſtimony. 1. He doth expreſly aſcribe to him a Kingdom,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>They are the ſame that are given to King Jeſus our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and agree to him onely. See Iſa. 9.7.</hi> Of the encreaſe of his Government and Peace there ſhall be no end; upon the Throne of David and upon his Kingdom to order and to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh it with judgment and with juſtice, from hence forth even for ever. <hi>Luk. 1.33.</hi> and he ſhall reign over the houſe of Jacob for ever, and of his Kingdom there ſhall be no end, <hi>Iſa. 9.6.</hi> Everlaſting Father, <hi>or,</hi> the Father of the age to come, <hi>as the Septuagint and the old Latin have it. Heb. 2.13.</hi> Behold I and the children which God hath given me. <hi>Micah 5.4.</hi> And he ſhall ſtand <hi>and</hi> ſeed <hi>[or rule]</hi> in the ſtrength of the Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he ſhall be great to the ends of the earth.</note> ſaying to him, <hi>THY KING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOM,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Thou rules and governs:</hi> now he that rules and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns in his own King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom muſt of neceſſity be an <hi>actual King.</hi> 2. He deſcribes to us the ſubjects of this Kingdom; who are nextly <hi>Joſ. Coal,</hi> and the Elders or Peers, whom he calls <hi>[us thy children]</hi> &amp; remotely thoſe <hi>to whom the Life of G. F. hath reached through the Elders to the begetting of them again to a lively hope,</hi> and they are ſaid to be <hi>MANY,</hi> by reaſon whereof he calls him the <hi>Father of many Nations.</hi> 3. He tells us what kind of power and authority it is, in which this King rules and governs, and that is, <hi>the Power of the Higheſt;</hi> a Spiritual and Divine po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, not like that of the Kingdoms of men. 4. We have here the ſtability of this Kingdom, <hi>Thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is eſtabliſh'd in peace.</hi> 5. The extent of it, <hi>The encreaſe thereof is WITHOUT END:</hi> It's a bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Kingdom. And 6. The glory of this King is
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:29497:28"/>
ſuch, that not onely the preſent Age, but <hi>Generations to come ſhall call him Bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">XXI. Henceforth I ſee not with what face they can blame any man for calling <hi>G. Fox King</hi> of <hi>the Quakers,</hi> (and that in the ſame ſenſe as Jeſus (that was dead) is the King of Chriſtians:) and the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders among them,<note place="margin">By this we ſee that <hi>W. Pen</hi> did not ſpeak unadviſedly, when he writes of his Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip in the <hi>Quakers-body,</hi> that <hi>it is an honour more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable than to be a compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Kings.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>his Children or Princes,</hi> in the like ſpiritual ſenſe; and ſo Peers of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: and all the other <hi>Quakers</hi> that adhere to them, <hi>Subjects of his Kingdom:</hi> for theſe denominations are moſt firmly built upon that Doctrine which themſelves approve. And ſo it's no marvel that they proceed againſt thoſe among themſelves, that will not ſubject them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to his conſtitutions, as againſt Rebels and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates. As for others that have not at all ſubmitted to his Government, which they preach up under the terms of <hi>the Light, Chriſt in man, Chriſt the Light, The Seed, A meaſure of Chriſt, The Spirit, The Infallible Guide,</hi> &amp;c. They account them <hi>diſobedient perſons, haters of the Light,</hi> Such as love darkneſs <hi>rather than Light, Of the World that lies in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Infidels,</hi> &amp;c. As <hi>Muggleton</hi> accounts them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers and reprobate perſons that do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him to be the great Prophet; ſo do the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> thoſe that ſubmit not to <hi>G. Fox,</hi> but under the ſpecious names aforeſaid: but they give as much ſpecial evidence of their being ſent of God one as another. They appeal to the Light in us; and when we condemn them upon moſt mature conſideration, they rail againſt us as partial Judges; <hi>W. Pen</hi> doth
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:29497:29"/>
profeſſedly number all that oppoſe them among Infidels, or worſe, and denyes them the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Believers; Nay, for ought I ſee he counts all of us that are married, <hi>Rogues,</hi> our Wives <hi>Whores,</hi> and our Children <hi>Baſtards;</hi> for he will not call <hi>John Pennymans</hi> Wife by his name, but by her Widow's name, conſequently ſhe is a Whore, and her Child a Baſtard, for all honeſt Women among us are called by their Husbands names. If he ſay <hi>John Pennyman</hi> was not married according to the Law of the Land; that exception will be as ſtrong againſt himſelf, who has had a Child by one, to whom he was never ſo married. Therefore the true reaſon of his abuſing <hi>John Pennyman</hi> and his Wife muſt be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were not married in the way of the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers;</hi> and the ſame reaſon is full as ſtrong againſt all that are not ſubjects of <hi>G. Fox's</hi> Kingdom. Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently he would call all our Wives by their former names, if he durſt: And <hi>W. P.</hi> is not ſingular in this matter, for other Foxonians have done the like in their Writings: ſo that it is matter of Judgment, not only of ſpecial malice, though perhaps it may be imputed to that cauſe, that he ſo deſcribes <hi>John Pennyman's</hi> Wife her inner apparel, as if he were as intimate with her as he is ſaid to be with <hi>Gulielma Mar</hi> — But <hi>M. Pennyman</hi> is better known and reputed for an honeſt Woman than <hi>W. P.</hi> is for a Man.</p>
            <p>But what occaſion did our Author give why <hi>W. Pen</hi> ſhould fall ſo foul upon <hi>John Pennyman,</hi> and eſpecially upon his Wife? A Woman who hath deeply ſuffered for their ſakes, and faithfully ſerved them <hi>for many years in whatſoever her hand found to do,</hi> (as ſhe ſaith of her ſelf in her Printed Poſtſcript,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:29497:29"/>
(a ſad rebuke to <hi>W. Pen</hi>) the Author doth not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion her, nor is there any one paſſage (that I know of) that relates to her; and that which he doth ſay of her comes in by head and ſhoulders. <hi>The Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker-Miniſters have changed that mean and plain ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit in which they came forth at firſt, into rich and fine clothing,</hi> ſaith the Author: <hi>He cries out againſt our Miniſters decent and clean apparel,</hi> (as if rich and fine, decent and clean were all one) ſaith <hi>Pen</hi>) which is <hi>but a better ſort of cover for his own ruſty Garb.</hi> Who ever thought to hear a Quaker blaming a Quaker for his mean Apparel? Then he ſuggeſts that againſt him, which I'm confident is the caſe of many among them, viz. <hi>That the Quakers mean Cloaths made up much of his convincement at firſt:</hi> but then immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately and on the contrary derides <hi>John Pennyman</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> his Wife for her <hi>Farrendine Gown and Sattin Bodice.</hi> Thus he lays about him like a mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; The Author has vext him, and he wrecks his fury upon <hi>M. Pennyman:</hi> We may ſee what a kind of Gentleman he is: a true Knight would have ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a Woman that gave him no offence, and not have ſtript her to her Bodice, and expoſed her in the open ſtreets with her Name and Crime in her fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head: but all this is ſutable to a Peer of <hi>G. Fox's</hi> Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. But as for <hi>J. Pennyman,</hi> he is one who for many years has had his Soul vext by ſeeing and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the things complained of by our Author, and ſuch like, inſomuch that he has often bore Teſtimony againſt them; and therefore they conclude him of the ſame ſpirit with the Author, which was ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to entitle him to all the reproach they could caſt upon him, which dealing of theirs with their ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:29497:30"/>
covering or denying the matters objected, and bold challenge to make them good, fell out to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of our Authors Letter, for thereupon <hi>May</hi> 30 1673, <hi>J. Pennyman</hi> went to the Quakers Meeting in <hi>Grace-Church-ſtreet,</hi> and there openly declares <q>that though he was wholly ignorant of either the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or printing of <hi>the Spirit of the Hat,</hi> yet know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many of the matters therein inſerted to be true, he was willing to give <hi>John Oſgood</hi> (who knew them as well as himſelf) and others a private meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to manifeſt the ſame, and alſo many other matters of as high concern and of as great wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which (ſaith he) for about theſe thirteen years my ſelf with ſeveral others in thoſe dayes bore a faithful Teſtimony againſt:</q> The next day <hi>W. Pen, J. Oſgood, J. Claypool,</hi> and <hi>W. Brend</hi> came to his houſe and demanded of him to give them a particular charge,<note n="*" place="margin">They would not grant <hi>John Whitehouſe</hi> a coppy of his charge, which <hi>John Boulton</hi> and others had drawn up againſt him.</note> which he ſoon drew up and ſent to <hi>W. Pen,</hi> containing twenty four particulars, many of which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated in theſe Papers. (The 23d againſt <hi>George Fox</hi> diſcovers his hypocriſie and dawbing, which we publiſh not, as <hi>W. P.</hi> doth any baſe Inſinuation, that may make his adverſary obnoxious to the Government) To which <hi>W. Pen,</hi> according to his wonted modeſty, replyes, that <hi>they wondred to ſee ſo empty an Account, after ſo great a charge publickly exhibited; that they had agreed among themſelves, that before they proceeded to a meeting, be ſhould let them know, if this were all be intended to inſiſt upon, and if the iſſue of that Tryal ſhould be the deciſion of the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:29497:30"/>
controverſy between them, they would not have their charge piece-meal</hi> with more to that purpoſe. To which <hi>J. P.</hi> returns, that he had done enough at preſent. Thus theſe great Champions evade the anſwering of this fair Challenge. And now, though our Author's name doth not appear, yet we have that which gives more vallidity to his Work, the publick atteſtation of a credible perſon perſonally given: For names to Books have been not ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom forged; and who knows whether <hi>W. Pen</hi> will publickly atteſt to all thoſe Pamphlets, and things in them, that are printed with his name? If he will, then let him hear what a judicious Country-Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man writes to his Friend upon the reading of <hi>The Spirit of Alexander,</hi> and <hi>the Winding-ſheet.</hi> W. P's <hi>words of</hi> J. P. <hi>are more ſcornful, than can be ſeem any pretender to ſobriety: His ſtomack is neither nice nor ſqueamiſh: He can (I ſee) talk at the rate of a Coffee-houſe Pamphleteer, and account it a piece of high ſelf-denial to ſet his name to his jerking anſwers.</hi> This man is more mild than that learned and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious man who upon the reading of his <hi>Winding-ſheet,</hi> gives him in his Letter the title of Buffoon, and much more of that import, which I do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VV. P.</hi> His treating of <hi>J. P.</hi> and his Wife in this manner puts me in mind of his calling it <hi>a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid lye, that they with the</hi> Papiſts <hi>prefer a looſe perſon before a Non-conformiſt: p.</hi> 15. for what are <hi>J. P.</hi> and his Wife, our Author and the other ingenious Quakers (whom they call Hat-men) any other but Nonconformiſts? whom yet he treats as Apoſtates, the worſt of men: ſo that his anſwer to that charge which he calls a horrid lie, proves it a clear truth,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:29497:31"/>
if there were nothing elſe (as there wants not enough) to bear evidence.</p>
            <p n="23">XXIII. Now for concluſion to this very unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent work, (which the benefit I hope many will reap from it, has put me upon) I ſhall further alledg ſeveral teſtimonyes, both out of <hi>G. Fox, VV. Pen</hi> himſelf, and divers other of their approved men, againſt <hi>the honour and reverence of the</hi> Hat, which now they impoſe, upon peril of all ſacred and civil privileges that are in their power to deprive their people of.</p>
            <p>King G. Fox. <hi>True Honour among the Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 8. <hi>The Honour and Worſhip with the Hat, and that humility (ſo called) is voluntary, and voluntary humility, and not of command by Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>P. 11. <hi>For the Hat is an earthly thing, and a thing below; and they that trouble, fine, impriſon about it, cannot chuſe but mind earthly things, and mind things below, and circumſtances, and cuſtoms, and faſhions of the world, and feigned humility in which there is no ſubſtance, which is below the Royal Seed, and the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and dignity of a man, and the honour above, and the Worſhip of God, and the true humility which goes before true honour that is above.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P. 13. <hi>Now is not Chriſtians worſe then theſe—who make ſuch a work and adoe about putting off their Hats, which are for the covering their nakedneſs? But the true</hi> Jews <hi>would not put off their Hats in the Synagogue, nor in the Temple,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:29497:31"/>1653. <hi>G. Fox</hi> and <hi>Rich. Hubberthorus</hi> Reply to the Northern Miniſters, in a Book called <hi>Truths Defence,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>P. 22. <hi>And when you read them</hi> [the Pſalms] <hi>Hats you keep on, and when you ſing them Hats you put off, and here you worſhip the works of your own hands,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>1653. <hi>G. Fox</hi> in a Book called <hi>Several Papers, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P. 5. <hi>And when they read the Pſalms, they keep on their Hats; and when they ſing them, they keep off their Hats; here they worſhip the work of their own hands: all ſuch practices we deny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About 1659, <hi>G. Fox</hi> To the Judges and Lawyers.</p>
            <p>P. 10. <hi>Now the Hat-Worſhip, that Honour, that Idol is ſet up by tranſgreſſors, but men that be in the Law of God which is over tranſgreſſion — they mind not the Hat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P. 25 <hi>Now puting off the Hat is but a cuſtom got up among the Chriſtians ſince the Apoſtles in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy, a vain cuſtom ſet up by traditions, which is a worſhip of Men and of the Beaſt, and honour below, and an Idol ſet up by Tranſgreſſors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P. 27. <hi>O what a covering of darkneſs is got over you! [ſpeaking of the then Miniſtry,</hi> &amp;c.] <hi>and of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice and hardneſs of heart and wickedneſs, that now in the Ancient of dayes, a Hat makes ſuch work with you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:29497:32"/>
               <hi>W. Pen.</hi> No Croſs no Crown, P. 7, 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixteen Reaſons why Cap-honour and titular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects are neither honour nor reſpects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reaſ. 1. <hi>Becauſe— if true honour conſiſts in Hats, Bows, or Titles, then are the moſt prophane and deboiſt the moſt civil, ſince moſt expert in thoſe vain Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, which is impoſſible.</hi> Pſal. 50.23. Iſa. 33.15.</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 2. <hi>Becauſe real Honour is a ſubſtantial thing manifeſted by obedience, which therefore cannot ſtand in invented geſtures — which it muſt neceſſarily do in caſe the ceremony of the Hat be an honour or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reaſ. 4. <hi>Becauſe honour properly aſcends, not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends, yet the Hat is near as frequently off to equals and inferiors, as to ſuperiors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reaſ. 5. <hi>If pulling off a Hat, or Title, were to pay honour, who ſo vile — that could not honour? but this is to make Honour (as ſuperſtitious men do Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion) to conſiſt in ſome external appearances,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Read more in his Book, which for brevity ſake I may not tranſcribe.</p>
            <p>J. Naylor, <hi>concerning Worſhip, Printed about</hi> 1656. <hi>God is a Spirit, and in Spirit is he worſhiped, not with Mens hands, not with bodily exerciſe, farther then by the eternal Spirit the body is exerciſed: ſo the imaginations, thinkings, and conceivings are ſhut out; all mans ways, mans times and forms, mans decency and orders are all ſhut out, and condemned with the Spirit in which God alone is worſhiped.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I ſhall produce the Judgment of eminent men among the <hi>Quakers</hi> concerning the very contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy about the Hat, after it was commenc't among them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:29497:32"/>
               <hi>Iſaac Pennington. Some Queries in the power and drawings of the Spirit of the Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Quer. 1. <hi>Whether this preſent miniſtration of life doth not point men to an inward principle there to wait for the Teachings of Gods Spirit within, and not to go forth into reaſonings about things (either from Scriptures or otherwiſe) after the manner of men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Quer. 2. <hi>Whether thoſe whom the Lord made uſe of to direct to this principle, did then tell us that when we were turned thereto, we muſt obſerve what comely or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were preſcribed by the Apoſtles in the Churches, and that they preſcribed them by the Spirit of God; and that if we were not found in the ſame comely orders, we were not led by the Spirit of God; or did they not rather tell us, that the Epiſtles of the Apoſtles were writ to the then preſent ſtate of the Churches, and that we were not to take up the ſame practices unleſs we were led there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by the ſame Spirit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Quer. 3.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>To this 3d Query</hi> G. White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head <hi>anſwers—the</hi> 5th <hi>of the</hi> 4th <hi>month 1663.</hi> This is an unreaſonable and impertinent Query, eſpecially as it is to in who are in the Miniſtry, for we never went about to limit the Spirit of the Lord, in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off or keeping on the Hat in Prayer, <hi>&amp;c. Will he now dare to diſown and puniſh men for that practice, which he acknowledges they may be moved to by the Spirit of the Lord? O ſtrange!</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Is the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off or keeping on the Hat in Prayer a thing of ſuch a nature, for the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord ſo to be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted about, as that he ſhall not,</hi> &amp;c. — <hi>may not the Spirit of the Lord in ſome of his choſen veſſels teſtify againſt it? Oh let God alone reign in Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Quer. 4. <hi>If this be
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:29497:33"/>
brought in as a comly order, is there not equal ground for bringing in all other things which the Apoſtles pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in thoſe days to the Churches, as comly orders alſo, and ſo ſetting up the outward Court again, which the Spirit of the Lord left out in the meaſuring of his Temple, and withdrew from?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. 5. <hi>Is not this the direct way to draw the mind into reaſonings about Scriptures, and from a ſimple waiting on the principle of Life, where the true peace and unity alone is preſerved, and ſo neceſſarily a beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting into ſeparation and diviſion? for it is not at this day different practices that divide, but a departing from the principle, and a propagating of unity by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings and conſiderations about things, where it is eaſy to err and run into uncertainties, and miſs of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of life and its leadings, which (if the Lord ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it to prevail) will bring that deſolation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach upon Iſrael, which the enemy otherwiſe never could.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far <hi>Iſaac P.</hi> who ſurely is a man as able to give an account of the <hi>Quakers</hi> principle as <hi>W. Pen</hi> the <hi>Novice</hi> in that way. If it be ſaid that <hi>Iſaac P.</hi> is of another mind now; that makes for us and not againſt us: for if he was for many years before a true <hi>Quaker</hi> and a great and approv'd Writer for that way of infallibility, and then for ſome years after profeſſ'd that, as their principle and doctrine, which he afterward recants; doth he not evidently give the lye to himſelf and doctrine? Can the Spirit of God reach a man for ſeven years together that he ought to keep off his Hat at Prayer, and then for the next ſeven years teach him that he may keep it on ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and teſtify againſt the conſtant keeping it off, and after that teſtify againſt that Teſtimony? what
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:29497:33"/>
blaſphemy would it be to aſſert this? And yet this is <hi>Iſaac P's</hi> caſe. Would to God he, and they that are concerned with him, would ſeriouſly conſider what firmer grounds he has in ſuch matters to believe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf infallible at one time more than at another? If it muſt be reſolved by the judgment of the Body, then for ever give over the Doctrine of Infallible Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in particular perſons; and betake your ſelves to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſe Characteriſtick Doctrin that is. But if every particular perſon is fallible, whereon ſhall the Infallibility of the Body be ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? but to proceed to ſome other of theſe infallible Teachers.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>John Crook the</hi> 22d <hi>of the</hi> 12th <hi>Mon.</hi> 1662. About Meats, and Drinks, Geſtures, and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, Habits, Times, and Places.</head>
                  <p>DEarly Beloved Friends — Meats are for the belly and the belly for Meats: the head is for the hat, and the hat for the head, but God will deſtroy and lay all theſe in the duſt. Know your liberty therefore as to theſe things in the Lord, as thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> below the life into which you are called; onely uſe it not for a Cloak, for envy or diſcord: for as we read of Cain and Abel, two men performing the ſame action, attended with the ſame circumſtances of occurrences and formalities, and yet the one accepted and the other rejected; In like manner may two perſons be found in contrary actions, poſtures or geſtures, and yet both accepted of God. — For if I ſhould lay a bond upon my ſelf therein, I tranſgreſs the liberty of the Spirit, either as to time, conſtanoy or place: or if another ſhould lay a bond upon me, or put a
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:29497:34"/>
yoak about the neck of the diſciples, this is no more juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable than the former, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We find</hi> John Crook <hi>and</hi> Edward Burrough <hi>alſo (a man great without controul) joyning in a Letter with</hi> John Perrot <hi>(the Head of the Hat-men) and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing their unity with him long after he had decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelf in the matter of the Hat.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thus they write:</hi> We are here [Newgate priſon] kept cloſe priſoners, but the bleſſed preſence of the Lord is with us, and we are all in dear love and perfect uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and our ſouls do rejoice in the fellowſhip with God, and one with another, in his love and life: and the Lord hath knit our hearts together in the happy unity, and the contrary is judged, and life and power reigns over all, Bleſſed for ever.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>About the year</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>1662.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>Edward Burrough.</item>
                           <item>John Crook.</item>
                           <item>John Perrot.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p n="24">XXIV. In the laſt place I ſhall alledge the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of <hi>Benj. Furly</hi> (a man of parts) concerning this controverſy of the Hat, as I find it given in a ſhorter abſtract of a large Paper wrote by him in behalf of himſelf and the <hi>Quakers</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> Dated from <hi>Rotterdam</hi> about the year 1663, and addreſt to <hi>George Whitehead:</hi> which tho' it is larger than might fit this Diſcourſe, yet I hope will recompence the Reader by a clearer ſtate of the controverſy among them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:29497:34"/>It runs thus:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>George Whitehead,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>THy Paper, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I receiv'd, and indeed cannot but admire at thy proceeding therein and dealing with me in that politick manner; but ſimplicity and innocency had better become thee and the profeſſion of the Miniſtry of Chriſt, and will alwayes be found the beſt Weapons and Armor; but thoſe that have neither Truth nor Right with them in their plea, muſt needs uſe ſuch weapons as are moſt ſuitable to their evil cauſe, and by which Truth hath alwaies been oppoſed, and the profeſſors thereof perſecuted: for verily, to my grief, I find thee in this thing walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the too too plain footſteps of all the falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets that ever got up into a carnal Authority, <hi>viz.</hi> to cloath the innocent and harmleſs ſheep in the skin of a wolfe, or ſome other ravenous beaſt, and then all will be out of love with them at firſt ſight; the ſheep will ſhun and avoid them, and the dogs run upon and tear and worry them. Thus thou haſt done whether ſimply or ſubtily, the Lord will judge; but thou haſt put me on the Garments of oppoſition, impoſition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yea of oppoſition againſt ſuch as in the freedom or motion of the Spirit of Life do put off their Hats in Paryer; which thing is far from mee, and that which I ſhall, as the Lord gives me opportunity and freedom, bear my teſtimony againſt in any perſon whatſoever.— And the Paper which I wrote ſpeaks no ſuch thing as thou wouldeſt impute to it, it ſpeaks not in the leaſt againſt any thing which any man is moved to from the Lord, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any man for doing as he is moved; nay, though he ſhould but ſo think and be miſtaken in his thoughts, I would not have him leave it till he ſees better. But I do only caution ſuch as do pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:29497:35"/>
it without any other ground in themſelves, as to the thing it ſelf, as to that groundleſs one of doing it becauſe others do it, and becauſe it hath been our cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtom and order ſo many years, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> — And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ng ſuch a Paper come forth from <hi>G. F.</hi> ſo harſhly and perverſly judging all about it <hi>as being entred into the Ranters principle</hi> (though we hate it as much as he can) <hi>and calling it a comely order,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to be out of which was a token of being out of the Spirit in which the Apoſtle did worſhip God.</hi> And knowing further that <hi>G. F.</hi> did as much break one part of that order (ſo called) in propheſying covered, and others with praying with Caps on their heads, for the Apoſtle ſaith every man that prayeth or propheſyeth (and <hi>G. F.</hi> in his Paper to the <hi>Dutchmen</hi> addeth, or ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) having any thing upon his head, diſhonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his head. I ſay, knowing and ſeeing this, I could not but lay theſe things before Friends, that they might not be deceived, by the example or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of any man. — But if any liſt to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious about it, and tells it is a comely order, and I muſt put off my Hat, or by him be judged to be out of the Spirit of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall rather chuſe to undergo his falſe judgment then defile my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence by any piece of will-worſhip which the Lord requires not of me—and tell him or them that the Church of God hath no ſuch cuſtom as to contend or impoſe in ſuch maters, but hath in this taught us, and that truly, that every member is to be guided by the meaſure of Life—in which alone the true unity and good order is.</p>
                     <p>And I am fully perſwaded of this, that if ever any ſeparation be, it will be through thy and ſome others Lording, rigid driving Spirits, — yet I cannot
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:29497:35"/>
but caution thee and all Friends, to keep to the motion of the Spirit of God in all things, and to act nothing by cuſtom, upon the account of being his People or the true Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For who or what made us to differ? and if we go without that, wherein do we again differ from others? <hi>and he can ſoon call them his people, and make them a people that are no people.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For it is not lawful for any man, or company of men, becauſe he or they are in the Spirit of God, and of the true Church, to do, or agree to do what they pleaſe, nor to make, appoint, preſcribe rules and orders for themſelves and all other the members of the ſame body, how or in what manner they ſhall worſhip God, and then walk in thoſe rules, whether the Lord leads them into them or no:— But if he or they ſhall go and do that which the Spirit and Life doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of him, it ſhall be ſaid unto him or them, who hath required this thing at your hands: And therefore very unreaſonable &amp; contrary to the known grounds and principles of truth is thy Query to us,—viz. <hi>Wherefore we do not go into the world and ſhew our teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and ſign againſt them in their Steeple-Houſes.</hi> For we can as little go into any of the Steeple-Houſes to be a ſign againſt them, as we can be conformable to any practice which ſome Friends may uſe — unleſs it be required of us. No manner of worſhip being true or performed aright further then it is performed in the guidings, leadings and motions of the Spirit both as to matter, manner, form and order.</p>
                     <p>And for thy ſaying, what do I know <hi>but the Lord may require the putting off the Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> now as he did Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to put off his ſhoe?</hi> I ſay, I limit not the Lord, nor diſwade any from obeying him, nor yet to leave this thing, that do but think it is required of them, but
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:29497:36"/>
what is this to them that know the Lord doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it of them? And tho' thou ſhouldeſt this day feel the Lord certainly leading thee to it, what's that to thee to morrow, unleſs thou haſt the ſame motion then alſo? yea if a man ſhould have found the Lord leading him ninety and nine times to a thing, if he ſhould do it once more in his own will, that once will be found to be will-worſhip and voluntary hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> — for he is as much an Idolator that goes before the power, as he that draws back or ſtayes behind is diſobedient. Therefore beware what thou doſt thy ſelf, and how thou leadeſt others to act blindly without their owne guide. Thou ſayeſt I accuſe <hi>G. F.</hi> for being of another mind than he was ſix or ſeven years ago; but thou doſt abuſe me in ſo ſaying: for I neither ſay nor can believe that he is really of another mind, but that he is to this day, and thou alſo of the mind (tho' ye unrighteouſly detain or conceal the Truth) that it is neither ſin againſt nor diſhonour to God for a man publickly to Pray with his Hat on, which both his and thy practice ſo long ſince (and ſtill in propheſying ſo) doth evidently ſhew. But when a man gives himſelf to partiality, to juſtify an unrighteous &amp; condemn a righteous thing, what confuſion is he not ſubject to utter, and what pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful ſtuff wil he not bring forth, as is this thy fond ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, viz. <hi>that the outward head muſt be uncover'd, becauſe all things are naked and bare before the Lord;</hi> and thy ſilly (or worſe) comparing <hi>the Elders caſting down their Crowns before the Throne of God to worſhip, with mens doffing their Hats to Pray;</hi> but ſurely thou art not ſo weak as thou ſeemeſt, nor doſt in thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience believe, that they did then doff their Hats, nor yet that thoſe Crowns were any viſible Materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls:
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:29497:36"/>
and yet very frivolouſly ſayſt, <hi>this was no Romiſh Tradition.</hi> O <hi>George!</hi> why doeſt thou thus dally in theſe matters? may not doffing the Hat as a peece of reverence and worſhip of God, be a Romiſh Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though that was none? May not a man doff his Hat to Pray, and yet keep his Crown and not caſt it down before the throne of God? and may he not wear his Hat in Prayer, and yet caſt down his Crown as the Elders did? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I fear this ſtrife is more for Maſtery and the Crown than for the thing it ſelf; and in Chriſt and his Worſhip no bodily ſervice of any member availeth any thing, but a new creature; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any covering is to be heeded, but that of the new man.</p>
                     <p>But if thou judgeſt us in this thing as weak chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, bear with us as ſuch, and abuſe us not, neither inſult over us, as being gotten up above us <hi>into the ſtate of Chriſt who never fell, and beyond the ſtate of Adam before he fell;</hi> and withal beware of thinking ſo of thy ſelf, — for this work of thine apparently comes from ſelf, and exalted above judgment, which God will bring down.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Thy true Friend <hi>Benjamin Furly.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Now I heartily beg it of the <hi>Quakers</hi> that they would ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly lay it to heart, <hi>How they can be aſſured of any motion or immediate revelation from God, concerning any matter of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief or practice, (not determinable without ſuch revelation,) ſo as to judge another perſon thereabout?</hi> Since they find ſuch palpable and acknowledg'd contradictions in thoſe things, both to one another and to themſelves, in the very chief men of their party. And I am perſwaded that all that know them will acknowledg that the Hat-men, and thoſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented with them, were far more conſiderable for abilities and endowments of every kind, than any the like number of Foxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians. For my part I wonder much what account thoſe that are fallen from their Principles among theſe, can give of their
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:29497:37"/>
ſo doing either to God or men. Indeed it's matter of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that any conſcientious and ſober man or woman ſhould yet adhere to a Body of People, whoſe Leaders are detected of ſuch groſs Contradictions and Enormities as theſe we have been treating of.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="order">
            <head>Here follows a Copy of <hi>George Fox</hi>'s ORDER touching the Slit in the Waiſtcoat, &amp;c. mentioned pag. 11.</head>
            <p>ALL Friends every where on your Signs ſet not up the image and likeneſs of any Creature in Heaven or in Earth, but by the power of the Lord keep down all the makers of ſuch things; for the ground of them is from the Heathen: But ſet up a <hi>Bed-ſtaff, Fire-ſhovel, Saw, Fork, Compaſſes, Andirons, Harrow, Plow,</hi> or any ſuch thing. And all Friends every where admoniſh one another, young and old, that ye do not run after the Worlds faſhions, which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented and ſet up by the vain and light mind; which if you do, How can ye judge the World for ſuch things? Away with your <hi>Skimmingdiſh-Hats,</hi> and your unneceſſary Buttons on your Cloaks and Coats, and on the tops of your ſhoulders behind, and on your ſleeves: Away with your long <hi>Slit-Peaks</hi> behind on the skirts of your Waiſtcoats, and ſhort Sleeves, puniſhing your ſhoulders ſo as you cannot have the uſe of your arms. Away with your ſhort black Aprons, and ſome having none; Away with your <hi>Vizzards,</hi> whereby you are not diſtinguiſhed from bad Women, and your <hi>bare-Necks,</hi> and your great needleſs flying Scarfs like Colours on your backs. And ſo ſet not up nor put on that which you did once with the Light condemn; but in all things be plain, that you may adorn the truth of the Goſpel of Christ and judge the World, and keep in that which is comly and decent.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>George Fox.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <p>Publiſhed with the conſent of divers credible Perſons, who will be ready upon any juſt occaſion to give in their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies concerning the matters of Fact herein contained, and at the inſtance of many,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By <hi>Francis Smith.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:29497:37"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
